who came to play this perfect round of军 insert Cassie neck
who came to play this perfect round of军 insert Cassie neck
replaces our
replaces our
Colleagues of the Intermediate Court and our good neighbors
各位中院的同仁 還有我們的好鄰居
good night everybody
各位晚安
we are very happy today
那今天我們非常高興
We invite you to our courtyard
我們請到我們院裡面
Director of the Agricultural Biotechnology Center
這個農業生物科技中心的主任
Dr. Citizen came to speak to us.
市民者博士來跟我們演講
Then this Director Shi, he was a few years ago in 2008
那這個施主任他幾年前2008年
We worked very hard to bring him back from Yan'an abroad
我們很辛苦的把他從國外延安回來
When he was abroad, he was in
他原來在國外的時候在
the elvo university
這個埃爾沃大學
Before this, he graduated from the Biology Department of our Tunghai University
在這個之前他是在我們東海大學生物系畢業的
Go abroad after graduation
畢業完以後出國
There should be soldiers, right?
應該有當兵吧 當完兵
Just to ask
問一下
Go abroad to Alvor University
出國去到埃爾沃大學去
this
這個
Studying for a Ph.D.
進修 拿到博士學位
Then went to Harvard to do research for a while
然後到哈佛做了一陣子的研究
Then he was invited back to be a professor by his alma mater
然後就被他的母校再邀請回去當教授
When it comes to this, there is also a director of the laboratory
當到這個還有一個實驗室的主任
very well done
做得非常的優秀
we were
我們那時候
Agricultural Biotechnology Research Center
農業生物科技研究中心
Also just being restructured
也剛剛正在重組之中
After several years of preparation
經過了好幾年的籌備
former preparatory office
以前的籌備處的處
can be regarded as the director
也算是主任
Director Yang Qingsun also worked for a long time
楊清孫主任也做了很久
Laid out the technology very well
把技術奠定了非常的好
After the director comes back
事主任回來以後
in Taiwan
在台灣
related to our agriculture
我們農業方面相關的
Together
一起
do it really well
把它做得非常好
with the Council of Agriculture
跟農委會
the farmer
農民
Course Basic Studies
當然基礎研究
are full of in-depth
都有滿深入的一些
practice
做法
so today we
所以我們今天
very happy to talk about this topic
非常高興來談這個議題
because of this issue
因為這個議題
now more and more important
現在越來越重要
we yesterday
我們昨天
in the yard now
院裡面現在
A recently established
最近也成立一個叫做
issues of sustainable development
永續發展的議題
sustainable development inside
永續發展裡面
Of course, this includes a lot. What you may be thinking is that
這個當然包括很多啦,大家可能在想到的是說
This climate change is causing many problems now
給這個氣候變遷,現在造成很多的問題
Agriculture has also been hit hard
農業也受到非常大的一個衝擊
Someone told me yesterday that if Taiwan did not have these natural disasters
昨天有人跟我講說,如果台灣沒有這些天災的話
Like this typhoon, the vegetables and fruits produced by our agriculture, etc.
像這個颱風來,我們的農業生產的這些蔬菜水果等等
It's all too much process
都是過程太多了
Well, our technology is actually very good.
那這我們的技術其實是很不錯的
Recently, in fact, you have also seen these bananas for sale.
最近其實各位也看到這些什麼香蕉的建賣
It made President Ma very nervous.
搞得馬總統也很緊張
so this
所以這個
I said we are very, actually very happy in Taiwan
我說我們在台灣是很,其實是很幸福的
We do not lack these agriculture
這些農業我們都不缺
But there are many countries that have food shortages and other problems
但是有很多的國家是有糧荒等等的問題
So this future agriculture
所以這個將來的農業
Must rely on these more advanced
一定要靠這些比較先進的
Technology can help us solve many problems
技術來幫我們解決很多的問題
recurring problem or
重來的問題或者是
drought etc.
乾旱等等
Therefore, Director Shi's research
所以這個施主任的研究
is an expert in this field
就是這一方面領域的專家
For the so-called adverse environment
對於所謂的逆境環境
This effect on plants
這種對於植物的影響
Adversity, you may not be able to understand
逆境各位可能比較聽不太懂
what adversity is
什麼逆境是什麼東西
because it is stress
因為是stress
In fact, a relatively simple
其實講一個比較簡單的就是
Liu Zhang and Vice President
劉璋和副院長
When I was the principal of Chuo University
那時候在中央大學當校長的時候
He suddenly likes the Middle East, Chinese and Western
他忽然很喜歡中東中西
He kept asking about Zhongnan papaya
那中南木瓜他一直問說
Why is there no flowering or fruiting
為什麼都不開花也不結果
their driver told him
他們的司機就告訴他
no problem you go get some nails
沒有問題你去拿幾根釘子
Nail that trunk
那個樹幹釘一釘
he asked
他就問
It really blooms next year
隔年真的就開花
that is stress
那就是stress
i think plants are in pain
我想植物很痛苦
you nail it to him
你釘子把它打到他身上去
Then he has to react
那他要去做一些反應
what you guys are eating
那你們各位在吃的這些
what black
什麼黑
Lian Wu what is it called?
連霧 它叫什麼
Lianwu of black pearl
黑珍珠的連霧
It was also discovered by none of the farmers
也是農民無一中發現的
A Phenomenon
一個現象 海水道冠
Lian Wu, which came out the next year, is very sweet and spicy
就隔年出來的連霧很甜很辣
that is also a kind of stress
那也是一種stress
But that's not easy to do
不過那是不太好做
Later, in those lands, they used seawater to crown
後來那些地 他們就拿海水去冠
Those lands can't be used later
那些地後來都不能用
So there should be other ways to do these stress
所以應該有其他的方法去做這些stress
that's us mayor
那是我們 市主任
Maybe I'll talk later, I don't know
說不定等一下會講 我不知道
Another area that he is very concerned about now is
另外一個領域他現在很關心的是
Orchid, our grandma orchid in Taiwan
蘭花 我們台灣的這個阿嬤蘭花
He has done a very in-depth research now
他現在做了非常的深入的研究
he may explain later
他待會也許會做一些解釋
so this future
所以這個 將來
Everyone depends on him for food and food.
各位要有飯吃的都要靠他了
So let's applaud him quickly. Come on.
所以我們趕快跟他鼓掌 來
good
好
Thank you Dean Wang Wu
謝謝王務院長
this introduction
這種介紹
I probably can't bear it
我大概承受不起
But I probably won't talk about much of my own research today.
不過我今天大概不會講很多我自己做的研究
But we should have plenty of time to ask questions
不過我們應該有不少發問的時間
so you can stay till the end
所以各位可以留到最後
Let's just ask me those questions
我們才就說問我那些問題
Then I didn't define what is called historical biotechnology at the beginning.
那我一開始也不先定義什麼叫歷史的生物科技
Then I hope that by the end
那我就希望到最後的時候
Let's come back to discuss my reasoning
我們再回來討論一下我這個道理
Why I choose the topic of my talk today as the prospect of biotechnology in history
為什麼我把我自己今天要講的題目定為歷史的生物科技的展望
In fact, the Science and Technology Advisory Group of our Executive Yuan was around 2000
其實我們行政院的科技顧問小組在2000年左右
just defined biotechnology
就替生物科技下了一個定義
He said that biotechnology is the use of biological programs
他說生物科技就是利用生物程序
Biological cells or their metabolites to manufacture products
生物細胞或其代謝物質來製造產品
Or scientific and technical personnel who improve the quality of human life
或改進人類生活素質的科學技術者
If you use this definition is a relatively narrow definition
如果你用這個定義是比較狹窄的定義
Use this definition to define what is biotechnology
用這個定義來定義什麼叫生物科技
if so
那如果這樣的話
Then let me start with the so-called green biotechnology
那我先把所謂的綠色生物科技
just set it as
就把它定為就是
Primarily using cells related to plants
主要是利用跟植物有關的細胞
or metabolize substances to make some products
或者代謝物質來製造一些產品
over the past 20 years
那過去20年來
That is to say, this so-called plant
就是說這個所謂的植物
agricultural biotechnology or
農業生物科技或者是
The most notable achievement of green biotechnology
綠色生物科技最顯著的那個成果
many people will notice
很多人都會注意到
I'm a so-called genetically modified crop
我就是所謂的基改作物
So my speech today will be based on the period
那所以我今天的演講就以正如期間
Let me introduce you first
來跟各位先開始介紹一下
GM crops
基改作物
but please
但請各位
If you have environmental protection against genetic modification
如果各位有環保反對基改
don't be nervous
先不要緊張
I will also explain at the end
到最後我也來解釋一下
In fact, it means
其實就是說
not necessarily that is to say
也不見得就是說
we do biotechnology
我們要做生物科技
Must rely on genetically modified crops
一定要靠基改作物
So let's use fast
所以先後讓利用快
we'll talk about it until the end
等到最後我們再來討論
problems in this area
這方面的問題
that so
那所以
Because the application of biotechnology is the most important thing I'm talking about
因為生物科技應用就是我講的最主要的
Most notable achievement at the beginning
一開始最顯著的成就
genetically engineered crops
就是以基因工程的技術來改造農作物
This technology actually has a very not great picture
這個技術其實有一個非常也不算偉大的畫面
But the very important picture is the so-called gene transfer technology
但就是很重要的畫面就是所謂的基因轉職的技術
This technology is not only available to those who make plants
這個技術不是只做植物的人有
People who work as animals or living things have
做動物的或做維生物的人有
current technology words
目前的技術的話
Because there are some viewers who are not living beings and are trapped
因為有一些觀眾不是做生物的被困
so let me introduce a little bit
所以我稍微介紹一下
all living things on earth
所有的生物在地球上的生物
Our genetic material is all on the so-called blue physiognomy
我們的遺傳物質都是在所謂的藍色理上
The blue body is the DNA of the so-called double bone
藍色體就是所謂的雙骨的DNA
There may be thousands of genes on a single blue body
在一條藍色體上可能有上千上萬的基因
We count each gene as a unit
每一個基因我們就算那一個單位
The word of the gene will go through the so-called detour
那基因的話會經過所謂的轉路
so-called RNA
就變成所謂的RNA
To RMA it will...
到由RMA它就會...
this is transfer, this is transfer
這個是轉移,這個是轉移
turn into protein
變成蛋白質
Most of the biological functions or structures
那大部分的生物功能或者是構造
that protein is the most important
那蛋白質是最重要
So you're going to modify a creature
那所以說你要改造一個生物
What you have to change is to make it
你要改的就是讓它
that is to say it is protein
就是說它蛋白質
production of a specific protein
某一個特定蛋白質的產量
or more or less
或比較多或比較少
or it doesn't make the protein in the first place
或者是它原先不製造這個蛋白質
you let it make this protein
你讓它製造這個蛋白質
That's the easiest way to do it
那最簡單有各種不同的方法
you can achieve this
你可以達到這個目的
The easiest way is usually to
那最簡單的方法通常就是
you changed the gene
你把這個基因改了
or if you don't want it to have this protein
或者是你如果不要它有這個蛋白質
You give this gene to...
你就把這個基因給...
give it to...we call NACAO off
把它給...我們叫NACAO掉
i will remove it
我就把它給除掉
Then if you want it to express a new gene
那你如果要它表現一個新的基因
a new protein
一個新的蛋白質
then you may use various methods
那你就也許用各種不同的方法
Insert this gene into this blue above
把這個基因插到這個藍色以上的
so that it can express this kind of a foreign gene
讓它可以表現這種一個外來的基因
Want
要啦
This technology is what we call genetic modification
這個技術就是我們叫基因轉值
By definition, it is a bent gene
定義的話就是將一個彎來的基因
into cells or individuals
轉入細胞或個體
The definition is simple
這個定義很簡單
help easier
幫忙更簡單
In total, it can be classified into these four types
總共現在歸類大概就是這四種
The latter three can probably be used in animals, plants or microorganisms
後面這三種大概可以用在動物植物或微生物都可以
This gene gun is actually a gun
這個基因槍其實真的就是一把槍
You're calling the gold one Lobarico
你就是把那個金質的我們叫Lobarico
tiny gold particles
很小的金質的顆粒
wrap that DNA on it
把那個DNA包在上面
And then you literally take a gun and shoot it inside the cell
然後你真的拿一把槍射到細胞裡面去
That is you can put this DNA
那就是你可以把這個DNA
cell passed to another cell
傳到另外一個細胞的細胞
These technologies are actually special instruments that you need.
那這幾個技術其實都是你需要的特別的儀器
and they are quite expensive
而且都蠻貴的
So if you are an animal, you need to transfer the value of the animal
所以說你在動物你要做轉值的動物
that technique is difficult
那個技術很困難
that would be expensive for us
那也會咱們貴
Then in the plant it has a special method
那在植物裡面它有一個特別的方法
we are called
我們叫做
Replanting method in the agricultural management circle
農管界的轉植法
Well, this is actually because we are doing plant molecular biology.
那這個其實是我們就是做植物分子生物
The technology written from nature
從自然界寫來的那個技術
Then the replanting method of the agricultural management circle
那這個農管界的轉植法
The most important thing is in the natural world, I think if you see
最主要是在自然界我想各位如果看到
you have that tree by the road
在路旁你有那個樹
Or if grass is not healthy
或者是草它不太健康的話
Things that often have a long flow will go off
那常常會長一個向流的東西會去脫
Well, this is actually the seed flow of plants.
那這個其實就是植物的種流
it's the plants
就是植物來
look at this
那這個你看這個
This is a very typical
這個就是一個很典型的
For this cancer, it is usually the same as our cancer cells
這個癌的話它通常就是跟我們的癌細胞一樣
It keeps growing where it shouldn't grow
它在不應該長的地方它就一直繼續長
So maybe you are sometimes
那所以也許你有時候是在
You grow more near the place
近的地方你長出更來
or are you there
或者是你在那個
this is long is a kind of that
這個是長的是一種那個
It's just a meristem without specialization
就是分生組織而已沒有特化
That's why it's happening in nature all day long
那所以說它這個自然界一天到晚都在發生
The reason why there is such a flow
那這之所以會有這種種流
that's because
那就是因為
Agrobacterium has this ability
農感菌它有這個本領
it's bacteria
它本身就是敘菌
a fungus in the soil
土壤中有一個敘菌
Agrobacterium
就叫農感菌
English called Agrobacteria
英文叫 Agrobacteria
It carries itself with its own blue body
它本身帶它自己有自己的藍色體
It also has a function we call
它也有一個我們叫做
Tumor inducing possum
Tumor inducing possum
It is equal to the carrier that you can self-cancer
等於就是你能夠自癌的載體
This carrier has a piece of DNA on it
這個載體上面有一段DNA
If you plant
那你如果植物的話
if there is injury
有受傷的話
It will infect the plant with this bacteria
它就會這個細菌就會感染植物
Then put this piece of DNA
然後把這一段DNA
sent to the cell goose of the plant
就送到植物的細胞鵝裡面去
then become plant cells
然後變成植物細胞的
part of plant blue body
植物藍色體的一部分
That one has a set of genes
那這一有一套基因
its set of genes
它這一套基因
Is it the same as our human cancer cells?
它跟我們人的癌細胞會有沒有一樣
It causes cancer cells to continue to divide
它會讓癌細胞不斷的分裂
Cancer cells then make some
然後癌細胞會製造一些
Compound, what about this Seo Joon
化合物 那這個敘俊的話
will use these compounds as its nutrients
會用這些化合物來當它的養分
So it's a natural phenomenon
所以說是自然界發生的現象
That is to say almost 30 years ago
那就是說在差不多快30年前
That is to say, some molecular biologists who work on plants
就是說有一些做植物的分子生物學家
they figured out a way
他們就想出一個辦法
Take this set of DNA from the so-called Agrobacterium
把這一套所謂的農感菌的DNA
replace it with harmless DNA
把它換成沒有害的DNA
That is to say if you have any DNA
那就是說譬如說你有任何DNA
you're going to put it in the plant
你要把它放到植物裡面去
you just replace this paragraph
你就把它來取代這一段
If so
那這樣子的話
then you can
那你就可以
That is to say, you are the first to select a target gene
就是說你第一個你選定一個你目標基因
Then you put it in the Agrobacterium
然後你把它放到農感菌裡面去
And then you put it into the plant cells by the Agrobacterium
然後你由農感菌把它放到植物細胞
Then you put the plant cells into the cultured genes
然後植物細胞你再放到培養基因
Then in words like this
然後在這樣子的話
It's easy for you to have so-called genetically modified plants
你給我很容易可以有所謂的基改植物
The reason why this genetically modified plant is so simple is
那這個基改植物之所以這麼簡單是
In addition to this agricultural sense coupon can send DNA to the cells of plants
除了這個農感券可以把DNA送到植物的細胞以外
Most plants also have a very important characteristic
大部分的植物還有一個很重要的特性
so-called tissue culture
就是所謂的組織培養
For the plant, you have given it the proper grower
植物的話你有給它適當的培養機
You can put its cells in an incubator
你可以把它的細胞讓它在培養機裡面
that is to say split
就是說分裂
Then after splitting, you change to a certain type of cultivator
然後分裂完以後你換某一種培養機
it will stick out its roots again
它又會伸出根來
Then you are changing to a certain type of incubator
然後你在換某一種培養機
it will
它就會
Grow this above ground leaf
長出這個地上部葉子來
So these two properties
所以說這兩個特性
Farm sense coupons can deliver DNA to plant cells
農感券可以把DNA送到植物的細胞
Then
然後
Plants themselves have the so-called ability to regenerate
植物本身又有所謂的再生的本領
so
這樣
stand up
起來
We do so-called plant molecular biologists you want to make a genetically modified crop
我們做所謂的這些植物分子生物學家你要做一個基改作物
In terms of animals, you do it one by one and we can do it at a time.
在動物的話你是一個一個做我們是一次可以做上限的
Just say it like this
就說這樣子的話就是
So you are the genetic antison of your plant
所以你歸常就是你植物的基因反子
It's rich and cheap
就是很濃郁很便宜
And it works and it's just not expensive
而且有效 而且就是不貴
So almost twenty years ago
所以說在差不多二十多年前
After this technology was invented
這個技術發明以後
Scientists at that time thought
那時候的科學家就覺得
This can be said to bring
這個可以就是說拿來
help with some agricultural issues
幫助一些農業上的問題
So at that time I thought those molecular biologists
所以那個時候我想當初這些分子生物學家
When I started doing it, I actually thought it was just saying
開始做其實都是覺得就是說
Because this is a relatively accurate plant species
因為這個是一個比較算是比較精準的植物域種
Because every time you change your genes
因為你每次換基因的話
one gene at a time and puts it in another plant
是一次一個基因把它換到另外一個植物裡面去
In fact, our ancestors did domain species
那其實我們老祖宗做域種
It has been done for thousands of years, tens of thousands of years
已經做了幾千年 幾萬年
The techniques they use are actually very similar
他們用的技術其實也是很像
It's just that they're replacing a segment, a whole segment of chromosomes.
只不過他們換的是一段 整段的染色體
They have no way to accurately time
他們沒有辦法來精準的時候
I just need to change a segment, a gene
我只要換一段 一個基因
They exchange entire chromosomes
他們換的是整段的染色體
So we're genetically engineered and we can
所以說我們基因改造 我們可以
So we don't have to put the diagnostic chromosomes all at once
所以我們不用一次放診斷的染色體
In fact, most breeding in nature is unsuccessful.
其實在自然界大部分的育種都不成功的
Because you change so many chromosomes, the creatures you create can't compete
因為你換那麼多染色體往往造出來的生物都不能競爭
Just can't match the original Parental Strength
就是不能跟原來的Parental Strength
is its original copy or parent that competes
就是它原先的副本或母本來競爭
So now 20 years have this technology
所以說現在20年年有這個技術
not only for researchers to do
不只在研究人員要做
Some so-called Multic Companies are also starting to do this
有一些所謂的Multic Company也要開始來做這個方面
In fact, there are several quite successful examples
其實有幾個相當成功的例子
The first is crops that are resistant to pests
第一個就是抗蟲害的作物
Pest-resistant crops are actually learning from nature
抗蟲害的作物其實也是學自然界
There is a kind of building coupon in nature
自然界有一種樹立券
It secretes a toxin that kills
它會分泌一種毒素,那會殺掉
most insects
大部分的昆蟲
In fact, GMOs existed before
其實有基改作物以前
farmers are already using
農民已經在用
that's them
就是他們
macrotrophs
大量養育菌
Then put Su Lixing's toxin
然後把蘇利興的毒素
separate it
把它給分離出來
Then sprinkle it into the sky
然後就灑到天裡面去
this way to kill insects
這樣來殺蟲
But this insecticide is very expensive
但是這個殺蟲一來很貴
later you are
後來你就是
The range of killing is sometimes uncontrollable
殺的範圍有時候不太能夠控制
Especially in European and American farms
尤其在歐美農場的
he sprinkled words with ash
他用灰濟灑的話
often spilled on
常常就會灑到
That is to say, the granddaughter who is near
就是說臨近的那個孫女
the next one is
臨近的那個就是
he didn't kill
不是他要殺的
that will kill
那就會殺到
may kill pests
也許會殺掉害蟲
So this is like cotton now
所以這個像現在棉花
and Hawaiian sugar cane
還有夏威夷的甘蔗
Many of them have Su Lixing's genes
很多都是有蘇利興的基因
in him
在他裡面
In this way, it means
這樣子的話就是說
He is more resistant to insects
他比較抗蟲
but
但是
because you can't
因為你不可能
if you just say
你如果就是說
You put the whole area you want to plant
你把整個你要種的區域
All insect resistant
全部都抗蟲
then soon
那不久的話
From immediately it will evolve its anti-comfort properties
從馬上就會演化出它抗以這個舒利性的性質出來
So they're doing GM lotus now or it's dry
所以他們現在在做基改蓮花的或者是乾澀的
They say you have a special proportion
他們就說你是有一個特殊的比例
For example, one tenth of you is the dryness of rock fairy
比如說你十分之一的是就是岩仙的乾澀
Ninety percent of this genetic modification
百分之九十就是這基改的
Then when you harvest like this
那你這樣子收成下來的時候
Once you come, you bug won't say that it has evolved drug resistance.
你一來你這個蟲就不會說演化出抗藥性
So this means that if you add this genetically modified crop to other methods of picking
那所以說這個就是說你如果這個基改作物加上你摘別的方法的話
You can probably be like one person, a forest is the control
你大概就可以就如一人某林就是控制
That is to say, you don't say that caused this, that is,
就是說你不會說造成這個就是說
This evolution is very fast
這個從演化速度特別快
that will bring disaster to you again
那又會造成你的災害
So the combination of the two is actually quite effective.
那所以說兩個合起來其實就是相當有效
So the dryness of Hawaii has probably been said for at least ten years
那所以說這個夏威夷的這個乾澀大概已經至少就說中了十多年
So far no major problems
到現在還沒有大的問題
That's because it's traditional farming in other ways
那就是因為這是傳統的農業在別的方法
Combined with biotech it becomes very ineffective
跟生物技術合併起來那就變成非常沒有效
Now China is growing a lot of cotton in the same way
現在中國大陸在大量種棉花也是這個樣子
The other one is anti-sand sweeping chicken
另外一個就是抗沙掃雞
In fact, traditional agriculture
其實就是說傳統的農業
Especially in the United States, it is not called a collective farm
尤其是在美國就是等於不叫集體農場
If it's a big farm
就是很大的農場的話
Are they all small farmers in Asia?
他們對不像在亞洲都是小農
So their kitchen storage skills are handy.
所以他們那個廚藏的廚藏技是用灰機的
Sprinkle it all in one piece
就一片這樣整個灑下去
so usually very serious damage to the environment
所以通常對環境造成非常嚴重的損害
So almost 20 years ago this Monsanto
所以差不多在20年前這個Mosanto
They did it with corn and soybeans
他們就那個玉米跟大豆就做了
Because they have a set of very good cooking skills
因為他們有一套非常好的廚藏技
That is BioDegradable
那就是BioDegradable
That is to say, it is not very residual
就是說它殘留性不高
But the problem is it doesn't just kill weeds
但問題是它不只殺草
It also kills corn and soybeans
它也殺玉米也殺大豆
So-called herbicide-resistant chickens found
找到所謂的抗殺草器的雞
put it in the corn or put it in the big meat
把它放到玉米或放到大肉裡面
So when it sells weed killer
所以它賣的時候就殺草器
sold with corn seeds
跟玉米的種子一起賣
Until now, it is the so-called run up ready corn
到現在為止就是所謂run up ready的玉米
This is it
就是這個
Then if you check the Council of Agriculture
那如果你去查查農委會
Most of the corn we import is this
我們進口的玉米大部分都是這個
So we have been eating for at least ten years
所以我們已經吃了至少十年以上
But this is actually if you evaluate it carefully
不過這個其實你如果好好評估的話
that's what it's really supposed to say
就是它其實應該就是說
still achieve its original purpose
還是達到它當初的目的
It's the one that makes COAG use less toxic
就是它那個讓農委使用毒性較小
There are also cheaper weed killers
還有價錢較便宜的殺草器
But in fact, Meng Sanduo earns the most money
但其實錢賺最多還是盟三多
Because it doesn't just sell weed killers
因為它不只賣殺草器
it sells seeds too
它也賣種子
The other one is disease resistance
那另外一個就是抗病害
Then I think this is the same as the anti-pest mentioned above.
那我想這個跟前面講的抗蟲害的
should be the same principle
應該是同樣的原理
that's it
那就是它
It can be naturally disease-resistant
既改做它能夠自然的抗病
or virus to drastically reduce pesticide use
或病毒大量減少農藥的使用
This is a relatively unsuccessful example
這個是比較不成功的例子
Because of the action of the plant's follower bacteria or fungi
因為植物的跟續菌或者是真菌的作用
very so-called specificity
非常所謂的有特異性
Usually it's what we call Gene Fire Gene Hituo
通常就是我們叫基因火基因海拓的事情
That is, your plants of a certain strain can only resist a certain kind
就是你某一個品系的植物就只能抗某一種
That is to say, inside the same kind of bacteria
就是說同一種的菌裡面
it's all kinds of bad
它有各種不同的糟糕
I can't speak Chinese
這個中文講不出來
just can't write
就寫不出來
It's just different species from different places
就是各種不同的地方的小種
Generally speaking, special strains are required
通常的話就是要特殊的品系
to resist this particular physiological race
才能抗這種特殊的生理小種
So you have to develop a really resistant
所以你要發展出一個真的能夠抗
Not so easy for all races
所有的生理小種不太容易
So this is a relatively unsuccessful example
所以這個是比較不成功的例子
The main reason is that our basic science is not good enough
最主要是因為我們基礎科學做得還不夠好
Because we don't yet fully understand
因為我們現在還沒有完全了解
that is
就是說
Why do you have to plant a gene
你這個為什麼一定要植物有一個基因
And then this cellulite has a gene
然後這個細菁有一個基因
Then the two have to interact
然後兩個人要互相作用
To determine whether there will be resistance
才能決定到底會不會有抗性
Although we have done this
這個我們雖然已經做了
I think the world doesn't know how many scientists have been doing it for thirty or forty years
我想大概世界不知道多少科學家做了三四十年
we know some but not all
我們知道一些但不是完全了解
So this is not a particularly successful example
所以這個不是一個特別成功的例子
But I think if this can be done
但是我想這個如果能夠做得出來的話
That's probably the ones I introduced earlier.
那大概也是就是會跟前面我介紹的那幾個
have the same material
有一起同工之料
The other is to say
那另外一個就是說
That this we can use the so-called biotechnology
那個這個我們可以用所謂的生物科技
to transform this important crop
來改造這個重要的作物
The so-called high nutritional value crops
那所謂的高營養價值的作物
And this one was almost twenty-five years ago
那這個是在差不多二十五年前
That is, a scientist in Switzerland
就是說瑞士的一個科學家
He just did a set of experiments
他就是做了一套的實驗
He can learn from that flower by taking the rice
那花學他可以就是把那個米
let him have a lot
讓他可以大量
high vitamin production
生產很高的維生素
Vitamin A
維生素Bitamin A
Then this is actually
那這個的話其實
He put this seed is unconditional
他把這個種子就是無條件的
It was unconditionally given to Huiser's country
當初無條件的要送給輝瑟的國家
That's actually very important
那其實這個非常重要
because in our asian country
因為在我們亞洲國家
especially in Taiwan
尤其在我們台灣
We think our vegetables are very rich
我們覺得我們蔬菜就非常豐富
So we don't think vitamin B
所以我們不覺得維生素B
What's so great about vitamin A
維生素A有什麼了不起
but in huiser country
但在輝瑟國家
because most of its children
因為它大部分的小孩
source of nutrition
就是說營養的來源
Mainly rely on staple food
主要是靠主食
so it's that
所以它的那個
Many people just have that vitamin A
很多人就是有那個維生素A
The lack of that phenomenon
不足的那個現象
that is, the disease
就是說那個病
If so, it will cause
那這樣子的話會造成
That is to say, the mans disease
就是說那個燕芒症
that science
那這個科學
That is to say, it came out of the first generation
就是說它第一代出來的
it is attacked that is to say
它被攻擊的就是說
How many catties of rice do you need to eat a day?
你要一天要吃幾斤的米
you have the possibility
你才有可能
that is to say, what you call
就是說達到你所謂的
enough vitamin A
足夠的維生素A
That this is what is called
那這個這一點被做所謂
That is to say link
就是說環節
GMO people keep attacking it
基改作物的人一直來攻擊它
That's actually a wrong message
那其實這是一個錯誤的信息
Because after ten years of his work
因為他做了十年以後
the one he does now
他現在做的那個
Let's say the amount of vitamin A he produces
就說他產生的那個維他命A的量
already high enough
已經夠高了
That is to say, as long as you treat yourself as an ordinary host
就是說你只要把你當成普通的主持
you can make this
你就可以讓這個
this do that gray state larvae
這個做那個灰州的幼蟲
can just say
可以就說
get enough gray lights
攝取足夠的灰燈
That's actually a very
那這個其實是一個非常
And this scientist didn't apply for anything
而且這個科學家他沒有申請什麼
patent he said
專利他就是說
You need to know how to give gray light to the government
你要懂得給灰燈的政府
But so far it doesn't work
但到現在為止還不能用
Why
為什麼
because one of the most
因為一個最
his earliest
他最早期
I used a very common carrier
用了一個很普通的那個載體
is a family
是一家
His patent is a
他的專利是一家
The very big Milote company
很大很大的那個Milote company
He has been refusing to unconditionally
他一直不肯無條件的
Give this to Louis and say
把這個給Louis出來說
Say this Yonago is going to be in Gray State
說這個米子要在灰州
don't need
就不用
That is to say, match him with that or that or something
就是說配他那個那個什麼
Patent Loyty's Ash
專利Loyty的灰
that to
那到
should go here
應該到這裡
These two years Burge Foundation should help
這兩年Burge Foundation應該有幫助
Now this rice should be ready soon
那現在這個米應該很快就實說可以
go to Huizhou
離去到會州去
But that's at least a decade behind
不過這已經是慢了至少十年
That's because many scientists say the benefits are good
那就是因為很多科學家就說利益很好
But in the end it's not really a matter of science
但是到最後其實已經不是科學的問題
Instead, it becomes a Polish or economic problem
而是變成Polish或經濟上的問題
That's a sad example
那這個是一個很可惜的例子
Because when he did it more than 20 years ago
因為他當初二十幾年前做的時候
I mean it's a party
就是說其實是個派對
It's a pity that it's not available until now.
那到現在為止才能用是有點可惜
Then do we have in Taiwan?
那我們台灣有沒有
Yes, we in Taiwan actually have several genetic modification effects
有 我們台灣也其實也有幾個基改作用
It's just that we're saying there's no clear Polish
只是我們就是說沒有一個明確的Polish
So can you go up until now?
所以能不能上到現在為止
Without the effect of genetic modification made by us in Taiwan, it can be listed
沒有我們台灣自己做的基改作用可以上市
Then that Dr. Zhenmincai from our Agricultural and Biological Center
那我們農生中心的那個臻民財博士
He said he did a few
他就說做了幾個那個
Do a few. Tomatoes can resist salt and liver disease
做幾個就是蕃茄可以抗鹽還有抗肝案
You may think that we don’t plant plants by the sea when we talk about salt resistance.
各位也許覺得說抗鹽我們又不把植物種在海邊
Why do anti-salt
為什麼要做抗鹽
Because we report that there are too many pesticides
因為我們回料還有農藥用多了
In fact, our soil has become slowly developed
我們的土壤其實都變成開始慢慢的研發
So you have to be persistent and good farmland will also become
所以你要執著好的農田也會變成
The ion content in the soil will be too high
土壤中的離子含量會太高
So salt resistance has always been a very hot topic
所以抗鹽一直是一個很熱門的題目
So Dr. Miantai successfully found several genes
所以在面台博士很成功的找到幾個基因
You put it in a tomato and you can see it resists salt
你把它放到蕃茄裡面去你可以看得到它可以抗鹽
This is another group of anti-hepatic cases
這是另外一組可以抗肝案
The other is Dr. Ye Xidong, former vice president of Central University
另外一個就是中心大學前副校長葉錫東博士
He is very famous for making papaya
那他非常有名的他就是做木瓜
Then his papaya's roulette virus
然後他的木瓜的輪點病毒
And that corporate virus
還有那個企業文病毒的
He has obtained double-resistant papaya
他已經獲得雙抗的轉職木瓜
The Council of Agriculture has approved him to conduct field experiments
農委會倒是有批准他可以進行田間試驗
But he also passed the food safety virus of our Department of Health
但是他也通過了我們衛生署的食品安全的病毒
But the farmer is not going to put it in Taiwan
但農友不是要把它放在台灣
Because Taiwan cannot be listed
因為台灣不能上市
This is available in India
這個印度可以上市
So this is probably for him to go to India
所以這個很可能是他給到印度去
Then Wang Mu just talked about a papaya
那王牧剛講了一個木瓜
You hit it and it will bloom
你把它打一打他就會開花
In fact, he has several types of papaya
其實木瓜他有幾種
that is to say he knows
就是說他大家都知道
Papaya bears the same plant as the magnetic bear
木瓜有熊的有磁的有磁熊同株
So if you're only a bear
所以你如果只做熊的話
It's useless for him to bloom
他開花都沒有用
But in stretch is in adversity
但是在stretch就在逆境
That is to say, you use iron nails or knock it a few times
就是說你用鐵釘或是把它敲幾個
you don't use nails
你不要用鐵釘
Actually just knock a few times
其實就敲幾下
That is to say, cut it off when he gets hurt
就是說把它割讓他有受傷的時候
You will let it sometimes its bear will transform back to female
你會讓它有時候它的那個熊的會轉變回雌的
So this is or transforms into female bear and pig
所以這個是或者是轉變成雌熊同豬
So at that time, it was not because it was afraid that it would become enlightened.
所以那個時候不是因為它怕了才會開化
but because it needs to be gendered
而是因為它需要有兩性化
Then naturally there is this evolution, it has this so-called Beauty in the system
那自然就有這個演化中它就有這個所謂Beauty in the system
It is to let you be in the reception because in fact, the most important purpose of all living things is to wear
就是讓你在因為其實所有生物它最重要的目的就是要穿中接待
Then if you only grow bears in one place
那你如果只有熊的在一個地方生長的話
Then it will find a way to change
那它就會想辦法就是要變
So this Juris Park and that have some basis
所以這個Juris Park它那個是有一點根據的
The papaya itself is actually you just need to give it environmental adversity
那木瓜其實本身就是你只要給它環境逆境
It's a little bit bearish and it's going to be late
它就有些熊的就會變遲的
Then it can be solved like this
那這樣子的話它就可以解決
The other one is Dr. Chen Longwang from our Institute of Academia Sinica
那另外一個就是我們中研院職位所的陳隆旺博士
All he did was make broccoli prolong life
他做的就是讓青花菜可以延長宿命
what he does is you turn this upside down
他做的就是你把這個是倒過來
Just put a gene in this broccoli
就是把這個青花菜裡面的一個基因
you take it off
你把它給拿掉
and after you cut it
然後你把它裁完了以後
This is Wild Time
這個是Wild Time
You can see he's just talking about circularizing soon
你可以看得到他就是說很快就環化
this is his
這個是他的那個
that is to say he did
就是說他做的
just say something like this
就是說這樣子的話
after you have accumulated
你才積完以後
the one he can have at the market
他可以在市場的那個
That is to say, the life span will be longer
就是說壽命會比較長
Then I want these slides
那我要我這幾張slide
have their condition
都有他們的condition
So you can also put it here
所以也可以在這裡放
the other one is
那另外一個就是
Dr Hong Dong-won from our Central Post Office
我們中央職位所的洪東源博士
Dr. Hong Dongyuan from Tian Jiaozhong
洪東源博士從田郊中
Find the two proteins that affect job-related allergic reactions
找到兩種會影響職務過敏反應的那個蛋白
Then you put these two proteins together with Xun Xing
那你把這兩個蛋白跟迅性在一起
he will cause
他就會引起就是說
Anti-disease mechanism that promotes duty
促進職務的抗病機制
that this
那這個
Huang Dengyong is my senior
黃鄧永他是我的學長
he with that
他跟那個
The scientist who made the golden rice mentioned above has the same attitude
前面講的做黃金米的科學家同樣的態度
He thinks biotech can do good
他覺得生物科技可以做好事
So he has a patent
所以他是有專利
But patents are not for sale
但專利不是要來賣
he is going to help others
他是要去幫助別人
So Mr. Feng is traveling around the world
所以馮老師就是周遊各國
Then he later discovered that in Africa, especially in Central Africa, the Yana generation
然後他後來發覺在非洲尤其是中非坑亞那一代
Bananas are their main source of telegrams
香蕉是他們主要的電文來源
In recent years, they have had that banana and that tail-adjustment disease
他們最近幾年就是有那個香蕉那個調尾病
Teacher Feng was very enthusiastic to apply.
馮老師就很熱心的去申請了
Woolen
申請了伍倫
Then train the scientists of this pit ya
然後訓練這個坑亞的科學家
teach them how to make GM bananas
教他們如何來做基改的香蕉
Later the BioGate Foundation paid
後來BioGate Foundation有出錢
It is to let the government in Kengya start to have a system to do this
就是讓坑亞的那個政府開始有系統去做這個
It means that we are the best in biology, so we can introduce this in it.
就是我們做生物最好的就能裡面就介紹這個
The results of this experiment by Mr. Huang Fangyong
黃方勇老師這個實驗結果
Then this Central Plains Institute was when the Dean of the Idea
那這個中原院就是在理念者院長的時候
patent
就無償把這個專利
hand him over to the government of the world
把他交給這個天涯的政府
so that they can experiment with this
讓他們可以做這方面的實驗
Well I guess this isn't really meant to help
那我想這個真的不是為了幫助
The issue of the laser in the countries of China and Wiener
那中威那幾個國家那個激光的問題
this is very important
這個是很重要的
Because intersecting is really what they host
因為相交真的是他們主持
if there is no medicine
要不一定沒有藥品
that is to say you have so far
就是說你到現在為止
And you can't find the insecticide that works
還你找不到有效的那個殺蟲藥
It's just that your chemicals aren't very effective.
就是你化學藥品不太有效
So this is a
所以這個是一個
It's actually a great contribution
其實是一個非常偉大的貢獻
That Mr. Huang just gave this for free
那那個黃老師他就是無償就給這個
So I told those few examples
那所以我講了那幾個例子
That is to say, those of us
那就是說當初我們這些
It is my predecessors and scientists of our generation
就是我的前輩還有我們這一代的科學家
We do these things in fact we feel
我們做這些事其實我們覺得
That is, if you're doing the right thing about so-called biotechnology
就是說如果說所謂的生物科技你做得對的話
is supposed to increase crop yields
是應該可以增加農作物的產量
can also reduce the godhead
也可以降低神格
And that means we want to minimize the damage to gold
還有就是說我們希望可以減少對黃金的損害
nutrition that can also improve human health
那也能夠改善人類健康的營養
The question is, are institutional plants really that safe?
問題在於難道就是說機構植物真的這麼安全嗎
there are two possibilities there are two you will worry about
那有兩個可能性有兩個你會擔憂的
The first one is whether it is practical or not safe
第一個就是說實用是不是安全
I think this should be safe
我想這個應該是安全的
because the food we eat every day
因為我們每天吃的食物
Eating foreign DNA
吃的都是外來的DNA
Including the DNA of animals, plants and bacteria
包括動物植物還有細菌的DNA
we eat them all
我們全部吃進去
And we humans have already
而且我們人類在地球上已經
That is to say, it has been developed for almost 100,000 years.
就是說研發快十萬年了
should be no problem
應該沒有問題
All the DNA you eat is digested
你吃外來的DNA通通被digest掉
So this shouldn't be the main problem
所以這個應該不是主要的問題
Practical and safe I think so far
實用安全我想到現在為止
Didn't say you did genetic modification
還沒有說你做基改
How about being poisoned after eating GMOs?
吃基改做就說的中毒怎麼樣
This should be a non-scientific question
這個應該是一個不是科學上的問題
It should mean that he and others
應該就是說他跟其他的
You're at about the same risk from eating other foods
你吃其他的食物的危險性差不多
I wouldn't say it's more dangerous
不會說比較危險
But there is one thing you should consider
但是有一個你倒是要考量
Will it have an impact on the ecological environment?
是不是會對生態環境會有影響
you want me to say depend
你要我說Depend
That is to say, it depends on what kind of genetically modified crops you make
就是說看你做什麼樣的基改作物
Some will spread if, say, you are patterned
有些如果譬如說你是花紋會傳播的
spreads far
傳播的就是說很遠
Then its patterns have certain properties
然後它花紋有某些特性
likely to interbreed with other species.
很可能會跟其他的種會雜交的話
that maybe
那也許
But the problem is we actually have the technology now
但是問題是我們現在其實有技術
will control this
會控制這個
We can just say let you get that to that
我們可以就是說讓你那個到了那個
The most important thing is that you passed it in.
那個最主要就是你傳進去了
We're doing this genetically modified crop
我們在做這個基改作物
A few genes should be placed in the middle so that you can choose
中間要放幾個基因讓你可以去選
Those genes are usually associated with antibiotics
那幾個基因通常都是跟抗生素有
can be antibiotics
可以是抗生素用
So you are afraid that this kind of thing will pollute the environment
那所以你是怕這種東西來污染環境
We now have the technology to remove it
我們現在有技術可以把它拿掉
After your genetically modified crops are made
你基改作物做成以後
The gene you want goes in
你要的基因進去
You can take these so-called vulture genes and remove them
你可以把這些所謂的雕把基因你把它拿掉
So this should not be
所以說這個是應該不是
It should mean that we can solve it now
應該就是說我們現在可以解決
But I think we still need to have a
但是我想我們還是需要有一個就是
Rigorous evaluation process and management information
嚴格的評估的程序還有管理的資訊
That is to say, if you have a
就是說你如果有一段
That is to say, if there is a very strict procedure
就是說有一個很嚴謹的程序的話
I don't think this should be a major problem
我想這個應該不會主要問題
But we need a check system
但是就是我們要有一個把關的制度
That's what I'm talking about now
那這個我現在講到現在
It seems to mean that your biotechnology is used to make genetically modified crops
好像就是說你生物科技就是拿來做基改作物
So I'm going to use a practical example now
那我現在要用一個實際的例子
Just use the tunnel example to convince everyone
就是用隧道的例子來 convince 來說明各位
That is to say, genetically modified crops are only part of biotechnology.
就是說基改作物只是生物科技的一部分
rather than all of it
而不是它全部
Then you if I hope that means you arrive
那你如果我希望就是說你到
You can feel it after I say this
我講完這個你可以感覺到就是說
If you can flexibly apply biotechnology
你如果可以靈活應用生物科技的話
you should be able to do well then
到時候你應該可以做得好事
than you mean you can
比你就是說你可以
What you have to worry about is a lot more
你要擔憂的是要多很多
So what I'm going to say now is
所以我現在要講的就是
That is to say, how do we use quality-based breeding
就是說我們怎麼樣用分質育種
To cultivate the quality of those saltwater waterways
來培育那些醃水的水道品氣
Then this salt water is actually a very important
那這個醃水其實是一個很主要的
that agricultural problem
那個農業問題
That world means agriculture every year
那個世界每年就是說農業
The loss caused by pickling water will probably stand in vain
因為醃水造成的損失大概站白之時
That is to say especially in that
就是說尤其在那個
in that is to say the main river
在那個就是說主要的河流的
The place where there are floods and floods
那個邊有洪水有泛濫的地方
this is the main problem
這個就是個主要問題
that unfortunately most of us
那很不幸的我們大部分的
the cultivated crop
那個栽培的農作物
After spraying with pickled water, you will lack oxygen
在塗 以淋醃水塗浪就會缺氧
So most of the crops
那所以說大部分的那個農作物
can only live
都只能那個活
survive for a short time
存活一小段的時間
Even if there are a lot of crops that will be flooded
那怕淹水的作物非常多
small amount of corn soybean
玉米大豆小量
wheat sorghum
小麥高粱
The flooded main do have a
那淹水的主要的做有一个
There is rice
有水稻
because you rice you can almost grow it in water
因为你水稻你几乎可以把它长在水里面
But in fact, in the various strains of rice
但其实在水稻各种不同的品系里面
It also has a different kind of collection for that flooded
它对那个淹水也有不同的那一种收集
Then this is an experiment done at the Philippine International Rice Research Center
那这个是在那个菲律宾国际水稻研究中心做的实验
It combines two different strains
它把两个不同的品系
The strain on the left is called FR-SERDIAN-A
那左边这个品系叫我们就把它叫FR-SERDIAN-A
Then the strain on the right
然后右边这个品系
AR-SIXTIFOR is actually similar to Thai bananas
AR-SIXTIFOR其实就是类似泰国香蕉
very popular in Southeast Asia
在东南亚非常流行的
And it has a very high yield
而且它的产量非常高
And you don't really need thinking
而且就说你也不太需要思维
resistant
有抗性
So in almost the whole of Southeast Asia are relying on
所以是在几乎整个东南亚都是靠
They are all planted with the so-called AR-SIXTIFOR strain of rice
都是种这个所谓的AR-SIXTIFOR这个品系的水稻
The experiment they did was you take these two
他们做的实验就是你把这两个
These two rice
这两个水稻
Soak the whole thing in water, not just the roots
整個泡在不是只有根部泡水
You put the whole spider in the water
你把整個蜘蛛都泡在水裡面
After soaking for a week
泡了一個禮拜以後
you take the water away
你把水拿掉
another week
再隔一個禮拜
You can see that this basmati rice is dead
你就可以看得到這個香米就死掉了
This FR setting A is still peeled well
這個FR設定A還剝了好好的
this is a pity
這個很可惜
This FR setting A rice quality is not very good
這個FR設定A米質不是很好
not very tasty
不太好吃
and it doesn't produce much
而且它產量不高
So farmers like rice
所以說農民喜歡中的米
just intolerable to flooding
就是不耐淹水
In southeast Asia especially in India's Heng River Cape State
在東南亞尤其在印度的亨河山角州
And this coal palace smoke water is a major problem
還有這個煤宮煙水是一個主要的問題
because every time it's summer
因為每次到夏天的時候
it has monshun creek
它有蒙順溪的
Just one cigarette lasts for several months
就一煙就是幾個月
So this is the main question
所以這個是很主要的問題
That's at the top of the Heng River in that Nagara
那在那個納加拉的亨河的頂端
You can see that there is a way
你可以看到有一種道
This is their local
這個是他們在當地的
and then later cultivated into cultivated roads
然後後來被培養成栽培道
Then this is called Deep Waterway
那這個叫深水道
Then you can tell it's oily.
那你可以看得出來這個是油齒的
then this is a person
那這個是一個人
you can see these roads
你可以看到這些道
it can grow taller than a person
它可以長到比一個人還高
Then this Daozi
那這個道子
Then your Dao is not a very good cultivation Dao.
那你這個道子也不是很好的栽培道
Because of its path, if you are planting
因為它這個道子你如果在種的時候
this is water
這個是水
if you drink hookah
你如果喝水煙的話
it has a reason
它有一個本理
It just grows taller than the river
它就是會長的比河水長的還要高
so it always has some leaves
所以它永遠有一部分的葉子
and cloth on the ground on the water
還有地上的布在水面上
what good is that
那這有什麼好處
Because of the effect of light ears, the silk protection cloth is oxygen
因為光耳作用的護蠶布就是氧氣
So you only need a part of your essence to be on the surface of the water
那所以說你只要有一部分的精在水面上
The effect of the light ear
那光耳作用一來
You can make oxygen and you can make sugar
你可以製造氧氛可以製造糖
So you have oxygen attack
所以你就有氧氧的攻擊
Then your silk protection cloth will have oxygen again
那後來你的護蠶布又會氧氣
so it can be passed to
所以可以傳到
so it will live
所以它就會活
But the problem is what to do when the water recedes
但問題是水退了怎麼辦
it's because it grows too tall
它就因為它長得太高
it just fell off
它就摔下來
You see we grow so short
你看我們栽培到那麼矮
makes sense
是有道理的
because it's going to knot and the knot is heavy
因為它要結碎結很重
so it can't grow too tall
所以它不能長太高
And its coldness is very high
而且它的細寒量特別高
It all went through our old ancestors
這都經過我們這個老祖先
Cultivated by President Yu
御總選下來的栽培到
it's so short
它那麼矮那麼並
makes sense
是有道理
It can bind so much water
它才能結那麼多水
So if this raw water arrives
所以這個生水到的話
When the water recedes, it really falls down.
水退了它真的就摔下來
its a week or two later
它一兩個禮拜以後
it starts to grow roots from here again
它又開始從這裡長根
The problem is the process of this growth
問題是這種生長的過程
its only good thing is that it survives
它唯一的好處是它活下來
let it live not very well
讓它活得不是很好
So it receives very little paper
所以它接了紙也特別少
So you're going to take this as
所以你要拿來這個當成
its main source words
它主要的來源的話
not sour
也不發酸
Which means you're unlikely to be able to live off of this
就是說你不太可能用這個來養活
Mongala countries those
悶加拉國家那些
so this is
所以這個就是
The greenhouse of the Agricultural Department of National Taiwan University
台大農業系他們的那個溫室
They planted this deep waterway
他們種了一顆這個深水道
Then this is to collect water
那這個是收集以水
That's about four meters tall
那這個大概四公尺高
you can see this way
你可以看到這個道
as long as you have water
你只要有水
it always grows on the water
它永遠長在水面
It has grown to four meters now
就已經現在已經長到四公尺
more than three meters
三公尺多
Then it should have a world record
那它世界紀錄應該有一顆
It seems to be seven or eight meters
好像是到七八公尺
in that
在那個
It's over there in India
是在那個印度那邊
there is a picture of this
有一張這個圖片
that so
那所以
Let's get these crops
我們去把這些作物
classify a little
稍微分類一下
salt water resistant
有抗鹽水
Afraid of salt water
有怕鹽水的
then the waterway
然後水道
There is also a little bit of salt water
也有稍微賣鹽水的
And Sectivo
還有Sectivo
then these two
然後這兩個
F-F-Sectivo
F-F-Sectivo
And this deep channel
還有這個深水道
will sell salt water
都會賣鹽水
that so
那所以
First
第一個
Actually you want
其實你要
if you want to leave
要要要欲走的話
your first question
你第一個要問的問題
That's why different crops
就是為什麼不同的作物
will have different water resistance
會有不同的耐水性
That's because I'm a teacher
那因為我當老師當冠了
so i tried this
所以我想這個
Today's section is about science
就是今天的一段就是跟科學
That is to say, it is related to the comparison made by our laboratory.
就是說跟我們實驗室做的比較有關的
I hope that means that if this doesn't work out,
我希望就是說各位如果這不能發落
It's okay, wait a minute and you can ask me
沒有關係等一下可以問我
But I should just keep it really simple
不過我應該就是把它弄得非常簡單
Then all organisms lack oxygen and we need nutrients
那所有生物缺氧我們都需要養分
Let's rejuvenate
那再養氣
when there is more oxygen
那再有氧氣的時候
The main source of energy for you and us is from Prado
你我們最主要的那個能量來源是從普拉多
aerobic respiration
那經過有氧呼吸
It generates 38 so-called ADPs
它會產生38個所謂的ADP
That's where our cells' energy comes from
那這就是我們細胞的能量的來源
Then if you are hypoxic
那如果你一旦缺氧的時候
into the so-called anaerobic respiration
就會進入所謂的無氧呼吸
That one glucose can only produce two ADP
那一個葡萄糖只能產生兩個ADP
there are two ways
那有兩個途徑
That one is through the so-called lactic acid type
那一個就是經過所謂的乳酸性型
one is alcoholic
一個是酒精性型
Most of all animals have passed through the so-called
那所有的動物大部分都是經過所謂
Once you are hypoxic
你一旦缺氧
undergoes what is known as lactic acid fermentation
會經過所謂的乳酸性型發酵
so why are we afraid
那所以為什麼我們怕
That is to say, a stroke in the brain is a lack of oxygen in the brain cells.
就是說腦部中風就是腦細胞缺氧
why can't it last
那為什麼不能持久
because
因為
Animals can only do so-called lactic acid flower effects
動物只能做所謂的乳酸性型花效
this is sour
這個是酸
So you suddenly acidify the cytoplasm
所以你一下子細胞質酸化
the cell dies
細胞就死了
dead in 20 minutes
20分鐘就死了
brain cells die
腦細胞就死了
So why is swelling so severe?
所以腫風為什麼這麼嚴重
Plants are a little smarter
植物的話稍微聰明一點
It will also take the lactic acid flower effect at the beginning
它一開始也是會走乳酸性型的花效
But once its cytoplasmic Ph
但是一旦它的細胞質的Ph
to 5.5
到了5.5
It will transform into a flower effect called alcoholic type
它就會轉換成叫酒精性型的花效
Sexualize it with alcohol and it will seep out
酒精性化它就會滲透出來
Most plant cells can survive in the absence of oxygen
植物細胞大部分都可以活在缺氧狀況下
can live for a while
可以活一陣子
So the first biological anoxic
所以說第一個生物缺氧
Oxygen free
就有氧無息
always oxygen free
總會無氧無息
second word in plant words
第二的話在植物的話
This is a cut surface of the root tip of a hardtail
這是一個硬尾根尖的痕切面
This is a normal hardtail tip
這是一個正常的硬尾根尖
You can see it this one we call Cortic rare
你可以看得到它的這個我們叫做Cortic rare
just very evenly
就非常均勻
Cell size is successful
細胞大小都成功
it's about the same and it's tight
它差不多,而且很緊密
Then you take the liquid that has been along the water for 18 hours
那你把沿水18個鐘頭的液體跟間
you make a cross section of it
你把它做一個橫切面
Then you can see that it has many
那你可以看到它有很多
In fact, this is where the cells die.
其實這個是這裡的細胞死掉了
that forms a tube
那形成一個管狀
one looks like a big circle
一個好像一個大的圓圈的樣子
If you look at it, this is the cross section
那你如果看,這是橫切面
Then if you fancy the section
那你如果看中切面的話
This is actually a tube
這個其實就是形成一個管子
Then I said before that the action of light will create oxygen
那我前面講過光而作用會造會有氧氣
So most plants have this ability
那所以說大部分的植物都有這個本領
That is to say, once its roots are flooded
就是說它一旦根部被淹水的時候
it wants to form a trachea
它想要形成一個氣管
Let it have more oxygen
讓它有比較多氧氣的功分
but the problem is that if the corn
但是問題是玉米的話
Actually you drown it for 36 hours and it dies
其實你淹它36個鐘頭就死了
So while corn wants to do this
所以玉米雖然想要做這個
it's too late
它已經來不及了
Because when your adversity comes
因為等到你逆境來的時候
it's too late for you to do it
你才要做來不及了
That
那
so
所以
but
但是
water arrived
水到了
Our strategy says that under normal conditions, you are born with tubular tissue
我們的災略道,你在正常的狀況下,天生就有管狀組織
If you cut the root of the water channel, there will be this kind of tubular tissue
水道你把牠切那根的話,本來就有這種管狀組織
So it is inherently slightly water-alongable
所以牠天生就具備有稍微有沿水性
So why can we, we can put the waterway inside the water
所以為什麼可以,我們可以把水道放在水裡面
But you can’t explain the villager, the FR setting class and the deep water channel
但是這個你就不能解釋這個鄉民跟FR設定類還有深水道的
Because all three of them have this ability, all three of them can breathe anaerobically
因為他們三個都有這個本領,他們三個都會無氧呼吸
will also form the tubular tissue
也都會形成那個管狀組織
Why is HR60 still not CUT, this FR setting is still CUT
為什麼HR60或還是不CUT,這個FR設定類還是CUT
This is also very CUT, so the International Waterway Research Center wants to know
這個也很CUT,所以國際水道研究中心就想要知道
Why is this villager different from FR settings? What is the difference between them?
為什麼這個鄉民跟FR設定類,它到底有什麼不一樣
They've been doing it since 1980
他們從1980年就開始做
sent them 20 years
發了他們20年
they finally found that is to say
他們終於找到就是說
In total five genes are
在總共有五個基因是
That is to say, let this FR setting be able to resist flooding
就是說讓這個FR設定可以抗淹水
but there is one most important
但有一個最重要的
That is, as long as you have this gene
就是你只要有這個基因
He's about 80 percent water resistant
他大概就有80%的抗淹水性
But he only knows which one to set
但是他只知道是在哪一條來設定
he doesn't know what gene
他不知道是什麼基因
So he has no way to want to be the general manager
所以他沒有辦法想要去做預總
At this time, it means that he was born in 2000
這個時候就是說他2000年
It was in 1996
就是在1996的時候
At that time, the so-called wedding paper pre-completion technology
那時候所謂的婚紙預總的技術
has become very mature
就已經變得很成熟
so there are a few
所以就有幾個
the University of California
就是美國加州大學
Riverside and this
Riverside還有這個
The family background of the two groups of Dennis Marriage School This team
Dennis婚校的兩組的家境這個團隊
It took them five years to find the gene for flood resistance
花了他們五年就找到了抗淹水的基因
This flood resistance gene actually
這個抗淹水的基因其實
Quite simply, because of the so-called biotechnology
很簡單,那就是因為有所謂的生物技術
Now the so-called molecular domain species actually has several methods
那現在所謂的分子域種其實有幾種方法
Then I will only introduce to you one of the more commonly used methods.
那我只跟你們介紹這個其中的一個比較常用的方法
Then the method is, for example, this is you
那這個方法就是譬如說這個是你
The FR design is also resistant to vaping, but it is not very good at keeping the output low
FR設計也會抗菸水的,但它不是很保持產量不高
Then this is the so-called Thai sweet potato
那這個是所謂的那個泰國香蕪
It is not resistant to vaping, so it says but it yields very well, and the rice quality is also very good
它不抗菸水,那它就說但是它產量很好,而且米質也很好
So what do you most want to do as a field breeder?
那所以你做域種的人最想要做的是什麼?
Let it go to the end, for example, this is an anti-smoke machine
讓它到最後,譬如說這個是個抗菸水的機
It hopes that in the end it will be planted by your last domain
它希望到最後就是你最後的那個域種出來的
all its machines
它所有的機
All of them are the Xiangwu machine, except for the smoke-resistant machine
全部都是這個香蕪的機,除了那個抗菸水的機
It's Qingben from this anti-smoke water
是來自這個抗菸水的清本
This Yanze is actually very simple
這個沿澤其實很簡單
You are the first one to compare the flood resistance and non-flood resistance
就是你第一個把這個抗淹水跟不抗淹水
After hybridization, it will have the so-called
雜交 雜交完以後它會有所謂的
recommendation that recommendation it will exchange chromosomes
recommenation 那recommenation它就會交換藍色體
Then you can choose from among your offspring
那你就可以從你後代中選出
It is flood resistant
它帶有抗淹水的
after you have this
那你有了這個以後
You can hand it back to this white guy again
你再跟這個白的再回交
If so
那這樣子的話
It will start to replace these blue ones step by step
它就會開始把這些藍的一步一步的取代
replace to the end
取代到最後
That is to say, you see that you have to recross almost eight times.
就是說你看你要回交差不多應該是八次
you can put other genes
你就可以把說其他的基因
All are the genes of this Thai countryman
全部都是這個泰國鄉民的基因
Except this is the flood resistance gene
除了這個是抗淹水的基因
This word in the Lord is very simple
這個在主上的話很簡單
it's not that easy
做起來沒有那麼容易
There is no way for them to do the traditional one
他們做傳統一種的話沒有辦法做
because they have no way of knowing
因為他們沒有辦法知道
Which gene is this
這個到底是哪一段基因
that do
那做
With the marriage paper biology, we can have each chromosome
有了婚紙生物以後我們可以在每一條染色體上
Find it is what we call a wedding paper label
找到就是我們叫做婚紙標的
So you just do some simple tests
所以你只要做一些簡單的測試
you will know
你就可以知道
For example, you are a hybrid, you do a few simple tests
比如說你這個雜交種你做幾個簡單的測試
You can know whether your section is blue or white
你就可以知道你這一段是藍的或者是白的
There is absolutely no way to do this in our traditional way.
這個在我們傳統一種上絕對沒有辦法做到
if you don't have so called biotechnology
如果你沒有所謂的生物技術
you can't do it
你絕對做不來
It is because of this technology
就是因為有這個技術
They quickly found the technology within five years
他們五年內很快就找到這個技術
This is from the International Watercourse Organization
這個是在國際水道組織
the one on their website
他們的網站上面的一個
You can see that this channel is twelve chromosomes
你可以看得到這個水道是十二條染色體
Then this is the FR setting that will resist smoke and water
然後這個是FR設定會抗煙水的
You see it's backcrossing and backcrossing a few times
你看它就是回交回交幾次
In the end they were like this for two years
到最後這樣子他們兩年
Because Huili Waterfront has three goods a year
因為匯利濱水道一年有三貨
So he seriously backcrossed them for two years and they found
所以他就很認真的就做回交兩年他們就找到
And of course some tests
當然還有一些測試
After finding this, you can easily find this season because of the molecular mark
找到這個以後因為有分子標的你也容易就找到這段季
This season so they spent half a year
這段季所以他們花了半年
This is what they do traditionally
這個是他們做的傳統的話
This is the most popular waterway in Mangara
這是悶加拉最流行的水道
but afraid of salt water
但是就怕鹽水
This is after salt water
這個是鹽過水以後
This is the FR setting class I mentioned earlier.
這個是我前面講的FR設定類
this is a hybrid
這個是雜交種
You see it backcrossed twice and five times
你看它回交兩次五次
It is equal to the result of ten times, you can see it
就等於是十次的成果你可以看得到
it will make it salt water resistant
它會讓它抗鹽水
This is the so-called molecular domain species
這個是所謂的分子域種
But it only takes half a year for you to use the genetic modification method
但是你用基改的方法只要半年
because they found the gene
因為他們找到了這個基因
They are called Savwan A
他們叫做Savwan A
This gene is in the FR setting class
這個基因就是在FR設定類裡面
Just inside the Thai mud
就泰國香泥裡面
Determine if the channel will be salt water resistant
決定這個水道會不會抗鹽水
the gene they found
那他們找到的基因
Put it in Thai incense mud for half a year
把它放進泰國香泥半年
as you can see it's very resistant to salt water
你可以看到它就非常抗鹽水
Then they, the three of us, they also took our Tainong No. 67
那他們,我三個人他們也拿了我們的台農67號
Tainong No. 67 is the most important one in Taiwan
台農67號是我們台灣最重要的那個
You're on the west coast and most of the east coast
你在西亞岸還有大部分東亞岸
the one that came out
那個預出來的中的那個
That our cultivation way in Taiwan
那個我們台灣的栽培道
They are all descendants of Tainong 67
都是台農67號的後代
Then they are also very afraid of flooding on Tainong 67
那他們也台農67號也很怕淹水
Then they also released the first half
那他們也放了這個上半年級
Natai Nong 67 now also has anti-flooding subsidence
那台農67號現在也有抗淹水的平息
You can get around at the International Watercourse Organization
你可以在國際水道組織繞得到
This is because the IHO Research Center is
這個是因為國際水道組織研究中心是
A research center under the auspices of the United Nations
聯合國手底下的一個研究中心
So you need none of these races for money
所以你需要這些種族都不要錢
means no profit
就是說沒有賺力
That is to say, everyone can
就是說大家都可以要
So actually that means
那所以其實那就是說
They've been doing this for twenty years
他們做了這這二十幾年來
That is, the progress has been rapid in the last five years.
就是最後五年進步很快
that is let them just say
那就是讓他們就是說
they did some experiments
他們做了一些實驗
Because besides being practical, you
因為你除了就是說實用以外
You now find this Thai township you will resist flooding
你現在找到這個泰國鄉你會抗淹水
Then let's make some machines
那我們做一些做機器
why do you want to ask
最想問的時候為什麼
Why is he resistant to flooding
為什麼他可以抗淹水
This FR is set to resist flooding
這個FR設定在抗淹水
Then you will find
那結果你會發覺
These strains that are not resistant to flooding
這個這些不抗淹水的品系
when it is flooded
它在一旦被淹的時候
it will continue to grow
它還會繼續生長
There's a downside to continuing to grow
那繼續生長有個壞處
it consumes energy
它消耗能量
so it quickly puts its
所以它很快就把它的
That stored nutrient is used up
儲存的那個養分就用光
so you flood it a week later
所以你淹它一個禮拜以後
you take it out again
你再把它拿出來
it dies
它就死了
Then this FR setting
那這個FR設定
or your jasmine rice
或者是你這個泰國香米
Coupled with this anti-flooding machine
再加上這個抗淹水的機
once you flood it
你一旦把它淹水的時候
it stops growing
它就不再繼續生長
It only maintains its most basic metabolism
它就只維持它最基本的那個代謝
Then it saves a lot of energy
那它這樣就節省了很多的能量
so once you put it
所以你一旦把它
when you flood it
你把它淹的時候
You submerge it for another month
再你淹它一個月
it won't die yet
它還不會死
you take it out again
你再拿出來
as long as it can continue the action of light
它只要能夠繼續光的作用
it survives again
它就又活下來
so it's a strategy
所以它這是一個策略
It should be regarded as a magnetic strategy
應該算是裝磁的策略
Even if you use salt water, it will not move, and then it can be replenished for a long time
就是你鹽水它就不動,然後就可以補很久
Animals also have this disadvantaged strategy, the tortoise
動物裡面也有這個劣勢的策略,烏龜
There are some turtles, it can't breathe for a long time
有一些烏龜,它可以不要呼吸很久
The main thing about it is that it shuts down almost all of its metabolism
它最主要就是它幾乎關掉它所有的代謝
So animals and plants have this Making
所以說動植物都有這個Making
Then you have to ask, the deep water channel, it seems that because of its deep water channel, it must not stop
那你要問,那深水道它好像因為它深水道一定不能停止
The deep channel is actually used for this or that
那深水道它用的其實就是這個是那個
I think I'll just skip this
我想我就跳過這個好了
The mechanism of the deep channel is just the opposite of this one
深水道它的那個機制,跟這個剛好倒過來
it is
它就是
This FR setting class it is salt water it does not move
這個FR設定類它是鹽水它就不動
Even if the salt water, this Thai villager who is resistant to salt water is
那怕鹽水這個抗鹽水的這個泰國鄉民是
It continues to grow, but it doesn't grow fast enough so it can't escape the water
它還繼續長,但它長得不夠快,所以它不能逃離水面
that this
那這個
So the raw water channel will make the giant gas grow, once it is sprayed to flood water, it will grow faster
所以生水道它會讓巨氣長,它一旦噴到淹水,它長得更快
So when we do molecular biology, we go back and ask
所以我們做分子生物,我們就回去問
That is to say, what is the mechanism?
就是說到底是機制是什麼樣
Then you can know that this research is very good
那你就可以知道,這研化非常妙
It uses exactly the same metabolic pathway
它用的完全是同一條的代謝的途徑
That is to say, this one is its main response when it is flooded.
就是說這一條是它主要淹水的時候的反應
There's going to be a residual suction, and then it's going to be a chain of
會有一個遺吸,然後它會有一連串的
Then this thorn will make your cells continue to divide, and then continue to grow
那這個刺就會讓你細胞繼續分裂,然後繼續成長
The section in the middle is the road taken by Thai villagers.
那中間這一段是泰國鄉民走的路
That is to say, it does not change, and it will continue to grow when it is flooded, so it is
就是說它不變,它淹水它就繼續長,所以就是
Then this is set by that FR
那這個是那個FR設定的
The way it goes is that it turns off its own metabolic records
它走的路就是它把自己的代謝記錄都關掉
so it doesn't grow so it survives
所以它就不長,所以它活下來
Then its mechanism is to use this growth technology
那它的機制它就是把這個有一個生長技術
it turns it off when it's flooded
它就在淹水的時候它就把它關掉
stop plant cells from growing
讓植物細胞不再長
flooded to
淹水到
It also controls the same metabolic pathway
它也是控制同一條代謝途徑
it just turned upside down
它剛剛倒過來
It allows this growth technique to produce more
它讓這個生長技術製造的更多
It makes more when it's flooded
在淹水的時候它就製造的更多
so you can tell
所以說你可以看出來
The place where the evolution temple is
演化廟的地方就是
In the same way, if you correct it and correct it, the effect will be the same.
同一條途徑你把它改正的跟改互的效果都一樣
are flood-resistant waterways
都是抗淹水的水道
So doing this kind of experiment is very rewarding
所以做這種實驗就非常rewarding
because you have practical value
因為你有實用的價值
because you can improve that is
因為你可以改善就是說
Now the rice is already in the ashes of the populace
現在這些米已經在灰的民眾
It should be released next year
應該是明年會上市
The Mengala strain I mentioned earlier
我前面講的悶加拉的品系
It will also be promoted in Mongara
也在悶加拉會開始推廣
How local farmers grow
由國際水道組織在交當地的農民如何種
The most important thing is this pre-made rice
最重要的是這種預出來的米
Its yield and quality are the same as those of the original strain.
它的產量還有品質跟原來的品系硬活一樣
They have been experimenting for three years
他們已經做了三年實驗
know now
現在就知道
So this gift is
所以說這個禮貨就是
have a practical use
有實際的用途
but in science
但是在科學上
You mean in basic research
你也就是說在基礎研究上
You also get a great deal
你也得到很大的報程
because of this
就是因為這個
just to let you know this
就是說讓你知道這個
so-called molecular mechanisms
所謂的分子機制
That's what we do
那這也就是我們這些做
The problems that basic researchers are doing
基礎研究人在做的問題
so maybe
那所以也許
then you can ask
那你可以問
Then we can not use this technology
那我們可以不會用這種技術
to make a super channel
來做一個超級水道
For example, if you start from the natural
比如說你從自然的那個
inside wild road
野生道裡面
or various materials
或者是各種不同材料
it has this
它有這個
For example, it looks very tax-heavy
比如說它長得稅特別多
And it looks so big on you
還有它長得你特別大
And it's anti-algorithm
還有它那個會抗密進
or smoke resistant
或者是抗菸的
it's being done now
它現在是有人在做
It uses this molecular labeling method
它就是用這種分子標的方法
take it
把它
want to put it
想要把它
That is to say it delivers this
就是說它交到這個
one
一個
for example for example
比如說譬如說
Our Tainong No. 67
我們台農六十七號
Maybe we'll go both ways in the future
也許我們將來就走這兩路
If this method
那這種方法的話
then you can just say
那你就可以就是說跟
Opponents of GMOs probably you can reach a goose shoe
反對基改的人大概你就可以達到一個鵝駝鞋
Because this method you don't use the base modification
因為這個方法你沒有用到基改
Although your end result is exactly the same
雖然你最後的結果其實一模一樣
But this is not every crop you can do
但是這個不是每一個作物你都可以這樣做
because you want to do this
因為你要做這種事
First of all, you have to have a lot of what we call seed relationship
第一個你要有很多的我們叫做種緣
So why is biodiversity so important?
那為什麼生物多樣性這麼重要
because you want to see what sex
因為你要看什麼性的
you must have this gene
你一定要有這個基因
In this species you have this gene
在這個種裡面你有這個基因
You can use this method
你才有可能用這個方法
if you don't
那你如果沒有
For example, the bananas you mentioned earlier
比如說你前面講我前面講的香蕉
It doesn't have such a good relationship at all, what should you do?
它根本沒有這麼好的種緣你怎麼辦
Then your GM crops are the only way
那你的基改作物是唯一的方法
So to say this from my point of view is to say
那所以說這個以我的觀點就是說
If it means that the genetic modification is not genetic modification
如果就是說其實這個基改不基改
Up to now, I personally think that it is not a scientific problem.
到現在為止我個人覺得已經不是科學上的問題
It's about political issues
而是說政治上的問題
that is
就是說
That is to say, the problem of acceptance in our society
就是說我們社會接受的問題
We scientists are responsible for this
這個我們科學家是有責任
We need to talk to the public
要跟社會大眾我們要要對談
That is, if we could have more conversations with that
就是說如果我們可以多多跟那個對談
Just face this method with an honest attitude of comparison
就用比較這個誠實的態度來面對這種方法
Maybe it means that some of our future crops
也許就是說我們將來某些作物
We can use sense to change
我們可以用機感來改
Some of you will feel that this technique is
有些你會覺得這種技術在
Then of course we use the words of this so-called molecular art
那我們當然就用這種所謂的分子藝種的話
that's it
那講到這裡那
seems to mean
好像就是說
This biotechnology can be used in this respect
這個生物科技就是可以用在這一方面
Then I am now at the end of my person, that is to say
那我現在最後面就是我個人就是說
In fact, I have been in the US for 30 years and only came back in 2008
其實我在美國30年在2008年才回來
Then I have been in the past almost 4 years
那我過去快4年就是
That is to say, we have direct contact with Taiwan's agricultural sector
就是說跟我們臺灣的農業界有直接的接觸
Then the following is my personal opinion
那下面是我個人的看法
I think it means that our biotechnology can be used in
就說覺得就是說我們生物科技可以用在
Our government actually sees the importance of this biotechnology
我們的政府其實也看到這個生物科技的重要性
So he proposed the so-called six emerging industries
所以說他提出了所謂的六大新興產業
There is the so-called golden agriculture and the biotechnology industry, the strength industry
有所謂的金字農業還有生物科技產業 力量產業
This is more or less related to agricultural biotechnology
這個都跟農業生物科技多多少少有關係
Our government has also created an interministerial so-called Agricultural Biotechnology Advancement Program
我們政府也成立了一個跨部會的所謂的農業生物技術推動方案
There is a goal in this plan
這個方案當中是有目標
In fact, want to help our country's economy
其實就是希望幫助我們國家的經濟
That is to say, to increase the output value of the agricultural biotechnology industry
就是說讓農業生物科技產業的產值能夠增加
but of course it's important
但這個當然是很重要
But is biotechnology only used once?
但是是不是生物科技就僅用一次
Then I think there is another aspect of biotechnology besides this.
那我覺得生物科技除了這個以外還有一個是
important task
重要的任務
this task is
這個任務就是
Because of the problems we face in Taiwan's agriculture
因為我們臺灣農業面臨的問題
It's not a matter of value
不是產值的問題
Because of your agricultural bioindustry
因為你農業生物產業
You will never your output value will never exceed the electronics industry
你永遠你的產值永遠不會超過電子產業
But it's actually more important than that
但是它的重要性其實比那個還要重要
There are so-called economists in our country
我們國家有這種所謂的經濟學家
That is to say, in that because of the rice
就是說在那個因為稻米
The problem of subsidizing farmers
要補貼農民的問題
Need to say that rice is so cheap
還需要說稻米那麼便宜
So cheap, just import them all
那麼便宜乾脆就全部進口
we don't plant
我們就不要種了
This sounds a little bit
這個說起來實在是有一點
Yes Just Say About the Basic Concepts of Food Security
對就說對糧食安全的基本概念
Economist who knows nothing
一點都不懂的經濟學家
because the world think about it
因為世界各位想想看
So rice is not a problem of greedy cats
所以就這稻米不是一個貪貓的問題
not a commodity
不是一個商品
Everyone, think about it, is there a country in the world?
各位想想看世界有沒有一個國家
Said to grow rice for sale
說專門種水稻來賣
rice to sell
稻米來賣
You can't find it. Countries around the world are successful in producing rice, so it is sold to other countries
你找不到,世界國家生產水稻有勝,它才賣到別的國家去
No country says that I specialize in selling rice, and the United States specializes in selling corn, and it doesn’t need to love corn
沒有一個國家說我專門做水稻來賣,美國專門做玉米來賣,它更不需要愛玉米
Because the corn it exports is not for food, it is eaten when it loses all, and the corn in it is used for other purposes
因為它出口的玉米不是吃的,它輸一空才是吃的,它中的玉米是拿來做別的目的
So soybeans are also this and that, but rice is not a commodity
所以大豆也是這個,那個都是商品,但水稻倒你不是商品
Once you say that there are some factors that affect the rice production, now Thailand will take it back and it will not export
你一旦就說有什麼因素影響水稻的產量,現在泰國就收回去,它就不出口
So we don’t want to grow rice in Taiwan because it doesn’t know about food security.
所以說這種我們台灣自己不要種水稻的,就是因為它不知道,糧食安全
That is to say, there is also this TU change at this level, so I will talk about these two
那就是說這個層面還有這個TU變遷,那我會講到這兩個
As for the sustainable use, I think President Wang Wu just said that our middle camp will probably slow down. In fact, we are already doing it, and we will do it in the future.
這個永續利用,我想這個王務院長剛剛講過,我們中營大概也會慢慢,其實已經在做,我們將來會
Let's just expand this area
就說擴大做這方面
Then why do I say that food security is very important
那為什麼我說這個糧食安全很重要
Because Taiwan's food independence was in 2008
因為我們台灣糧食自主力在2008年的時候
About 32% to 33%
大概是32%到33%
So far this year, 30% of it has been determined
那到今年為止已經演定30%
shares
股類
Don't say we have enough water
也不要說我們水到夠
We import a lot of stocks
我們進口非常多的股類
use it for other purposes
拿來做別的目的
We now have less than 30% of our autonomy
我們現在我們的自主力也不到30%
world
世界
Europe
歐洲
U.S.
美國
they subsidize their farmers
他們補貼他們的農民
kind
種
grow grain
種穀物
we subsidize our farmers
我們補貼我們的農民
don't plant
不要種
Nasyune
那修根
don't want
不要
Don’t think that pruning roots is cultivating land
大家不要以為修根是在養地
After a long time of pruning
修根久了以後
where you will
你那個地就會
would be useless
就會沒有利用價值
because no one to take care of
因為沒有人去照顧
you will have soon
你很快就有
yes there is that
有有有那個
The quality of the soil will become very poor
土壤就會那個那個品質就會變得很差
and this
那還有這個
The other one is that many of us
那另外一個就是我們很多的
The excellent agricultural land becomes what I call a dog house in Yilan
優良的農地就變成在宜蘭那邊我叫它是狗屋的
It's like a farmhouse, a small farmhouse that even dogs can't live in.
就被人家就好像是農舍一個一個小小的連狗都住不進去的農舍
Our farmland is constantly being lost
我們的農地一直不斷的流失
The worst thing is that Taiwan is not a miscellaneous grain that cannot be grown
最糟糕的是台灣不是不能種的雜糧
we had twenty years ago
我們二十年前有
But because Taiwan's land chick Yale replaced our miscellaneous grains with corn and soybeans, we needed special varieties.
但是因為台灣地雛雅樂代我們的雜糧要種玉米大豆這一類要特別的品種
All the people we pre-planted are lost because our government does not plant them ourselves
我們預種的人全部流失因為我們政府不自己種
Those of us who preseeded are all lost
我們那些預種的人全丟了
Then you have to turn back and say that now because the feed is very expensive, we are now saying that we will start growing our own grains
那你現在要轉回來說現在因為飼料非常貴我們現在說要開始自己種雜糧
We need to retrain our pre-seeds not those of us who do molecular biology
我們要重新培養我們的預種人才不是我們這些做分子生物
It’s about pre-planting in the front. We don’t have these skills. Most of the people who don’t have high school
而是到前裡面去預種的我們沒有這些方面的人大多高兩都沒有
And everyone is in their seventies now
而且人都現在都七十幾歲
So it will increase, this is our food security
所以它衝多來,這個是我們糧食安全
Because once you have any situation that affects food production
因為一旦你有什麼狀況影響糧食生產的時候
Let's not look at such a low production value
我們就不要看產值這麼低
You can survive without a computer
到時候沒有computer你可以活下來
I don't have rice to eat, I'll see what to do
沒有米吃我看著怎麼辦
So food security is a big problem for Taiwan's agriculture
所以糧食安全是我們台灣農業一個很大的問題
Another company not far away
另外一個企業不遠圈
Everyone thinks maybe it means softening for 100 years
大家想也許就是說軟化100年
only increase a degree or two
也只不過增加一兩度
Will it really affect agriculture?
真的會對農業有影響嗎?
So I'm also asking this question
所以我也在問這個問題
So I'm asking this question now
所以我現在就問這個問題
Will corporate changes really affect Taiwan's crops?
企業變遷對台灣農作物真的會有影響嗎?
The first one is that I have tweeted with many farmers in Taiwan.
第一個就是我跟台灣的很多農推
There are also many agricultural transformation factories in Taiwan
台灣也有很多農改廠
They are directly lower limit and farmers
他們是直接低限跟農民
Our rice has three major diseases
我們的水稻有三大病害
white leaf mushroom disease
一個叫做白葉菇病
Dao Le disease
一個叫稻樂病
The other one is called dragon mushroom disease
另外一個叫龍菇病
Dragon mushroom disease has no effect
龍菇病沒有影響
There is no medicine, but it is relatively rare in Taiwan
沒有藥劑 但在台灣比較少
There are medicines for Bai Ye Gu's disease and Dao Le's disease
白夜孤病跟道樂病有藥
But our farmers often spray pesticides until they pass out
但是我們農民常常灑農藥 灑到昏倒
It's because of the medicine they're going to spill
就是因為他們要灑進的藥
these two
這兩個
We have some strains in Taiwan
我們臺灣有一些品系
It is the strain introduced from Taiwan 67 Medicine
就是從臺灣67藥引出來的品系
against certain bacteria
會抗某一些菌
So our farms and factories have their tasks
所以我們的農台廠他們的任務
just to tell the farmers
就是要告訴農民
For example, which strain of rice do you want to plant in the next few years?
比如說你未來幾年你要種哪一個品系的稻
You can compare against Dowle's disease
你就可以比較抗道樂病
Comparable against white night disease
可以比較抗白夜孤病
They told me it seems like the last ten years
他們跟我說好像最近十年
I said before that you promote a strain
就以前就說你推廣一個品系
about ten years
大概可以維持個十年
They feel that the past ten years
他們覺得過去十年
That is to say, this cycle is getting shorter and shorter
就是說這個cycle越來越短
their speculation is that
他們的推測是說
Because of the increase in average temperature
因為平均溫度增高
The speed of this evolution is accelerated
這個續進演化的速度加快
is this real
這個到底是不是真的
so you're going to explore this
所以你要去探討這個問題
another this problem is very serious, because no one will do it for us
另外一個這個問題是很嚴重,因為沒有人會替我們做
Because Taiwan is here, this is the dimension of the Yangtze River
因為台灣在這裡,這個是長江的維度
All the countries south of the Yangtze River speak the second language, called Indica
長江以南所有的國家種的是再來語,叫Indica
Because it is a subtropical species
因為它是亞熱帶的品種
The strain north of the Yangtze River is considered to be a relatively temperate strain, called Japongi
長江以北的算是比較溫帶的品系,叫Japongi
Taiwan was occupied by the Japanese for 50 years, so the Japanese developed a
台灣被日本人佔了50年,所以日本人在台灣發展出
This strain of red rice means that we are a large temperate species in a subtropical country
這個紅來米的品系,就是說我們是亞熱帶的國家種溫帶的大物
If you grow like this, your germs will be completely different from others
那你種這樣子的話,你的病菌就跟人家完全不一樣
That is to say, Professor Wang Qiangsheng of Chung Hsing University
那就是說中興大學的王強生教授
He introduced 21 strains from the International Waterway Center, which are resistant to 21 kinds of bacteria
他從國際水道中心引進了21個品系,就是抗21種的菌
The farm collects the bacteria of white leaf mushroom disease from all over Taiwan
農事所收集我們台灣各地的白葉菇病的菌
he took three whole parties
他拿三個全黨
including eleven none
包括十一個 沒有一個抗
Three fungi of white leaf mushroom disease in Taiwan
我們台灣的三個白葉菇病的菌
Then we sequence the three bacteria
那我們把那個三個菌給定序出來
I found out that you use this Pingtung as the boundary condition
我發覺你以這個屏東為界化的條件
The east comes from the Philippines
東邊是從菲律賓那邊飄過來的
The west side is more similar to Japan and South Korea
西邊是跟日本跟韓國的比較像
But he has evolved his own set of chances of healing
但他又演化出他自己的一套治病的機率
so we don't do it ourselves
所以我們自己不做
no one will do it for you
沒有人會幫你做
Because our bacteria are different from others
因為我們的菌跟別人都不一樣
So now Professor Wang Qiangsen uses this
所以現在王強森教授就用這個
With Tailong No. 67, he gave it to
用臺龍67號他把它給
Give someone to find out who can resist
給有一個找出可以抗
Rice strains of white leaf mushroom disease in Taiwan
我們台灣的白葉菇病的水稻的品系
then we are doing this now
那我們現在也在做這個
So this has something to do with the warming
所以說這個就跟那個暖化有關係
Because you if the experiment we're doing right now is
因為你如果我們現在在做的實驗就是
The past ten years collected by our farm
我們農事所收集的過去十年
Designed GIRL from all over Taiwan
從台灣各地設計了GIRL
we are now working with them
我們現在跟他們合作
Every year we also collect GIRL in the same place
每年我們也在同一個地方收集GIRL
we can see how fast it evolves
我們就可以看它演化的速度
It can prove that the climate becomes warmer
它就可以應證氣候變得溫度升高
Will it affect the acceleration of the evolution of bacteria?
會不會對病菌演化的速度加快有影響
So I think I'll tell you the answer in 10 years
所以我想10年以後我再跟你們講答案
The second time you are blooming and bearing fruit in the waterway
第二個你在水道開花結果的時候
If you are too hot
你如果溫度太高的時候
it turned out to be an empty bomb
它結出來是空爆彈
It will affect the quality of its rice grain
它會影響它那個米粒的品質
Everyone, when you go to the market to buy
各位你到市場去買的時候
This is what you should buy
你要買的話是應該是這種
each one is transparent
每一顆都是透明的
This is normal
這個是正常的
It is a waterway with high nutritional value
是營養價值高的水道
Have you seen many of these
那你有沒有看到很多這種
opaque we call them agronomists
不透明的我們叫他們做農藝人
This is called a heart guard
這個叫護心板
This is from an empty bomb.
這個是空爆彈接出來的
Then this is when you are blooming
那這個就是你在開花的時候
During the so-called development period you experience abnormal temperatures
在所謂的開發這段期間你碰到溫度不正常
you will affect the outcome
你就會影響那結果
So they have a system to determine that
所以他們有一套系統來斷定就是
The quality of rice grains
米粒的品質
Therefore, high temperature will also affect the quality of rice grains.
所以高溫也會影響米粒的品質
another output
另外一個產量
The director of the aspect center of our middle school
這個我們中院院方面中心的主任
Liu Shaocheng did a string experiment
劉少成做了一人串的實驗
Over the past few decades in Taiwan
我們台灣過去幾十年來
Our high temperature average
我們的高溫平均溫度
Little change in Taiwan but one thing
在台灣的變化不大但有一點
our evening
我們晚上
temperature increase
溫度增高
Ip Man's increase rate is much higher than other countries
葉問增加的比例比別的國家要高很多
The other is the temperature difference between day and night.
另外一個就是溫差就是白天晚上
The temperature difference also becomes smaller
溫度的差異也是變得比較小
because it's hot at night
因為晚上熱了
The words of plants play a role in the daytime
植物的話白天性逛了作用
At night, only respiration
晚上的話只行呼吸作用
if your temperature is too high
你如果溫度太高
it breathes
它呼吸作用
In theory, it should be higher
理論上應該也是比較高
This will affect its output
這樣的話就會影響它的產量
International Rice Organization in the Philippines
在菲律賓的國際水稻組織
they did the experiment
他們做了實驗
in their laboratory
在他們的實驗室裡面做
If you find that your average temperature at night has increased by one degree
發覺你晚上的平均溫度增加一度的話
10% reduction in production
產量減百分之十
Taiwan over the past 100 years
台灣過去一百年來
Our average leaf temperature is two degrees
我們的葉溫的平均值是兩度
Did you say it affected the output?
你說有沒有影響產量
There is no experimental proof
也沒有實驗的證明
But I am from the Agricultural Department of National Taiwan University
但是我從台大農業系的
The Times Received by Mr. Lu Sen
盧森老師那裡接來的時代
Only ours is 9599697
只是我們這個是9599697
We rice this is our project goal
我們稻米這個是我們的計畫目標
This is our actual output
這是我們實際的產量
You can see the goal of our project
你可以看得到我們計畫的目標
Much lower than our actual output
比我們實際的產量都要低很多
He estimated the goal of the plan
他估計這個計畫的目標
It means how much area we will plant this year
是說我們今年要種多少的面積
So we expect that under normal conditions
所以我們預計正常狀況下
how much output should he have
他應該要有多少產量
You see two consecutive years
你看連續兩年
In fact, his newer data keeps falling
他其實比較新的data一樣一直往下降
Is it affected by Ye Wen?
是不是葉溫影響
Elevated leaf temperature affects rice yield
葉溫升高影響水稻的產量
Maybe but that's all we need to ask
也許但這個都需要我們去問
So our concentrated environment in Taiwan
所以我們台灣的濃縮環境
Rice is not the only problem faced
這個問題面對的不是只有水稻
Most concentrates face the same problem
大部分的濃縮物都面對同樣的問題
Because global warming will cause high temperature
因為全球暖化會造成高溫
For example, its average temperature increases
比如說它的平均溫度增加
Increased leaf temperature
葉溫增加
The temperature difference decreases, and the other is the increase in extreme climate
溫差減少,另外一個就是極端的氣候增加
It means that you have more days with strong wind and heavy rain
就是等於是你有大風大雨的日子增多
So the plant was originally living in its original climate
所以植物本來活在它原來的氣候底下
it has some adaptability
它有一定的適應性
It is now due to environmental changes
它現在因為環境變遷
Because the most important thing about Taiwan is that our terrain is very special
因為台灣最主要是我們的地形很特別
So some changes are completely different from continental country changes
所以有些變化跟大陸型的國家變化完全不一樣
So we also hit the steel shore and we go along the water
所以我們也會碰到鋼岸也會沿水
There are other issues such as the use of oxygen temperature and water smoke
還有其他的問題比如說像氧溫利用還有水之煙
This is the standard that our crops face
這個都是我們這個農作物面對的標準
What about you
那你怎麼辦
The first one I think is someone who does biotechnology
第一個我覺得就是做生物科技的人
This is a very important question
這個就是一個很重要的問題
In addition to the previous biotechnology industry, which is of course important
除了前面的生技產業那個當然重要
and that we can definitely do
而且那個我們絕對可以做
For example, that we already know how to do
比如說那個我們已經知道怎麼做
This is certainly worth pursuing
這個當然是值得繼續推展
Are we facing this problem
這個問題我們有沒有在面對這個問題
I think our government is probably starting to think
我想我們政府大概開始想到
that's them
就是他們
The year 2010 is the main direction of the agricultural science and technology forward-looking issue that was set last year.
2010年就是去年才定的叫做農業科技前瞻議題的主要方向
You can see that I listed a few that are now out.
各位可以看到我前面列了幾個現在出來的
It's on their government radar
就是在他們的在政府的 radar 上
This is why agricultural biotechnology also needs to face these problems
這個就是農業生技也需要來面對這些問題
This CCTV safety food safety
這個央視安全 食品安全
This promotion of the farmer's beard probably means
這個提升農民的鬍子大概就是說
It's not just scientists
應該不是只有科學家的
This should be the whole
這個應該是整個
That is to say, no matter what the social humanities and economics
就是說不管社會人文經濟的什麼
And this job, I think everyone should come in.
還有這個工的我想都應該要進來
and these few
還有這幾個
And this so-called sustainable utilization of production resources
還有這個所謂的生產資源的永續利用
As far as we're concerned, you do what you can
我們而言,就是你做你有什麼辦法
Because you seem to be talking about problems now, do you have any countermeasures?
因為你現在好像講的都是問題,你有沒有對策
Then I think the first one is you, because the research we have been doing is actually very simple
那我想第一個就是你,因為我們做的研究一直做的其實是很簡單的
In fact, I am working along the water
我其實我本身是做沿水的
So what we do is very simple, what to do when you lack oxygen
所以我們做的很簡單,就是你缺氧的時候怎麼辦
But now the plants in this field face not only flooding
但現在在這個田裡面的植物,它面對的不是只有淹水
It is faced because usually Taiwan flooding is down
它是面對的,因為通常台灣淹水是下減
So it usually faces high temperature and lack of oxygen
所以它通常面對的是高溫還有缺氧
Few people do this, and most people do experiments in the laboratory at a temperature of more than 20 degrees.
這個很少人做,大部分人在實驗室做實驗都是二十幾度
So the results of the experiment we did, if you want to go to the field to do it, probably most of it won't be needed
所以我們做了那實驗的結果,如果要到田裡去做大概大部分都用不著
So those of us who do basic research have to come back and ask questions in different ways
所以我們這些做基礎研究的審核就要回來問問題用不同的方式
That is to say, if you see the environment changes now, then you know the problems you may face
就是說你現在看到環境變遷,那你知道你可能面對的問題
we're going to find out
我們就要去了解
For example, can you train this to warm the predictions of the two lipid groups?
比如說你能不能培養出這個來暖化兩脂群的預測
Well, this should actually be a big challenge.
那這個其實非常應該是很大的挑戰
Because you are not only afraid of the heat
因為你不是只怕高溫而已
Are you still afraid of the difference between its night temperature and day temperature?
你還怕它晚上的夜溫跟白天的溫度的差距
That's a problem we've never faced before.
那這個都是以前我們從來沒有面對的問題
Then there are ice insect moxa, Huang Zhiying, water, and sheep adjustment
那還有冰蟲艾、黃志英、水分、羊分調節
It seems that I haven't mentioned this all the time.
那這個好像一直我沒有提到
But it's actually a serious problem
但其實這個是一個很嚴重的問題
water
水
We all complain that this industrial age uses up a lot of water
我們都埋怨這個工業期用掉很多水
Taiwan's agricultural water use is also very serious
那台灣農業用水也很嚴重
they also use a lot of water
他們也用很多水
Do you think water is needed?
那各位覺得水到需不需要水
You grow water so much that it actually lives well without water
你種水到其實不用水它活得好好的
Planting water is because you plant it in water because it has
種水是因為你把它種在水裡面是它有
It can mean that you can grow weeds
它可以就是說你可以培養雜草啊
and that one
還有那個那個
Canals can survive without water
水道沒有水還是可以活得很好
It's just that it may not be very productive
只是它產量可能不會很高
So now at the Center for International Waterways Research in the Philippines
所以現在在菲律賓的國際水道研究中心
They're starting to breed a new generation of waterway seeds
他們開始在培育新一代的水道種子
is that you use what they call Dry Cartigation
就是你要用他們叫做Dry Cartigation
It is to be planted in the sweat field
就是要種在汗地裡面
This is totally different from before
這個跟以前完全不一樣
Because if you want to sweat, you can't make a difference
因為你要種汗地你就不能差量
also use fools
也是要用傻子
So besides cultivation techniques, you
所以說你除了栽培技術以外
you have a new breed
你還有新的品種
You can still grow well that way
在那種方式底下你還是可以長得很好
We in Taiwan, I think we should also go this way
我們台灣我想也應該走這個路
Because for example, if we use water for your waterways
因為我們如果比如說你水道的用水
don't take that long
你不要用那麼久
For example, you don't want two and a half months
比如說你不要兩個半月
If you only let it last a month
你要是只讓它前一個月
Then save the water for three minutes
然後就把水你省三分鐘後的水
see what happens
那看會怎麼樣
I want to do research on this
我想這個方面的研究
none of us are doing it yet
我們都還沒有人在做
This needs to be done in the Tenriya
這個是需要實際上到那個天理屋去做
So these are the ones we should develop
所以說這幾個就是我們應該要研發
There is also the so-called resistance to adversity
還有所謂的抗逆境
So one of our current ideas is
所以我們現在的一個idea就是
We are tantamount to using biotechnology
我們等於是要用生物科技
we are not relying on the original
我們不是要靠原來的
Because of these environmental factors caused by the current environmental changes
因為現在這個環境變遷所造成的這些環境因素
Some plants have never been touched
現在有的植物都沒有碰過
So you have these sources
所以你要有這些種源
That is to say, you have to go to the wild to find wild species.
就是說你要去野外找野生的種
It may be difficult to resist
可以有抗的這種大概很難
The best thing we should do now is to use this so-called biotechnology method
最好我們現在就是要用這所謂的生物技術的方法
to create to create these various strains
來create 創造這些各種不同的品系
Then we have an early warning
然後就是說到時候我們有一個預警的
Early warning and monitoring system
預警還有監測的系統
For example, we can predict the next ten years
比如說我們可以預測未來十年
maybe not now
也許現在可能沒有
Maybe what will happen to our Taiwanese companies in the next few years
也許未來幾年我們台灣的企業會是怎麼樣
We can generalize this kind of system that we have experienced
我們可以推廣這一類我們就體驗出來的體系
This is of course in the planning stage.
這個當然都是在規劃階段
but we already have teams that want to start doing their own thing
但我們已經有團隊要開始做自己方面
So I think this should be what I'm going to explain today.
所以我想這個應該就是我今天要解文的
I think the role of the Academia Sinica in the field of agricultural biotechnology
我想這個中研院在農業生技化場所要辦的角色
I think we have quite a few really good research energy
我想我們有不少非常優秀的研究能源
Also has various expertise
也有各方面的專長
See the main direction of these our forward-looking topics right ahead of us
看到我們正前面的這些我們前瞻議題的主要方向
I think our Academia Sinica should have at least these aspects
我想我們中研院應該有至少在這幾個方面
we all have strengths
我們都有著力的地方
In fact, we have been doing it since last year.
其實從去年我們就已經開始做了
Let's say it combines the Agricultural College of National Taiwan University
我們就說結合了台灣大學的農學院
There is also our Agricultural Center and we have a teacher in the post office
還有我們農生中心還有我們有一位職位所老師
Then another economics student
然後另外有一位經濟學員
We set up a big research team
我們成立了一個很大的研究團隊
Just to do what I said earlier
就是要來做我前面講的那一件事
there is
就是有
This is the goal of our research
這就是我們的研究的目標
We also recently communicated with the International Water University Research Center
我們最近也跟國際水大研究中心
Signed one is Number 2, etc.
簽了一個就是Number 2等
By our COA students
由我們農委會的學生
come to do research team
來做的研究團隊
We are also research team
我們也在研究團隊
Signed one is Number 2, etc.
簽了一個就是Number 2等
by our Council of Agriculture
由我們農委會
That is to say, put some sutras
就是說放一些經會
IWU Research Center
放在國際水大研究中心
Then our scientists in Taiwan
然後我們台灣的科學家
You can go over there to do experiments
可以到那邊去做實驗
means we get there
就是說我們到那裡
you can use this money
就可以用這筆錢
separated from the scientists there
跟那裡的科學家分出
Then this is actually a
那這個其實是一個
that is not easy
就是說不太容易
That is to say, it is actually quite an important achievement.
就是說其實滿重要的成就
Because the research center of the International Water University
因為國際水大組的研究中心
an organization under the United Nations
是聯合國的底下的一個組織
that said earlier
那在前面講的
The previous president, the previous president was
前一任主席,前一任的president是
He doesn't dare to formally communicate with Taiwan whatever the Chinese mainland says.
中國大陸講什麼他就不太敢跟台灣的正式交流
A German was changed as president last year
去年換了一個德國人當president
Then you are willing to formally sign NHR with us
那就願意跟我們正式簽NHR
So our scientists in Taiwan can start now
所以我們台灣的科學家從現在開始可以
That is not only we have a team
就是說不只我們是有一個團隊
There is a formal cooperation contract
就是有正式合作的合約
They also see that Academia Sinica has resources
他們也看中研院有個資源
So they are also willing to cooperate
所以他們也願意合作
We hope that at least in the next five or ten years
我們希望至少在未來五年、十年
We can contribute in addition to the Academia Sinica in the biotechnology industry
我們可以除了在生技產業中研院有貢獻
We prefer to face the
我們更希望在這個面對的
the problems he faced in agriculture
他農業所面對的問題
Because it's actually a really big challenge
因為其實是一個非常大的挑戰
We hope we can have some contribution
我們希望我們能夠有一些貢獻
then i think i'll stop here today
那我想我今天就停在這裡
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Mayor for your wonderful speech
謝謝市主任的精彩演講
We have some time to open up your questions
我們有一些時間開放大家的問題
Do you want to ask him for advice?
有沒有要跟他請教的
Mayor
市主任
I listen to talk and I have an association
我聽連講我有一個聯想
We will also talk about the excavation of health food later.
我們後面也會講一個保健食品的開挖
Taiwan now our civilian clothes
台灣現在我們那個民衣
Many peasant children including me
很多農家子弟包括我
Don't eat rice that isn't farmed
不種田的米都不吃
Afraid of fat
怕胖
so many of us now
所以我們現在很多人
don't eat rice at all
根本不吃米
So our colorectal cancer
所以我們大腸癌症
Already senior for three years
已經高級前三年了
Are we the technology method you mentioned just now?
我們是不是剛才你講的科技的方法
can put this rice
可以把這個米
Our electric paper
我們那個電紋紙
that saccharification
那個糖化
Carbohydrate or reduce
碳水化或減低
that keeps it nourished
那保持它的營養
Like what you said just now, people will be able to promote that
像你剛才講說人家會就可以推行那個
buy them extra high
買他們比特別高的
Then encourage people to eat rice
那鼓勵人家吃米
You can also check this
也可以檢提這個
Dachanghai
大常海的
The proportion of Dachanghai is a little bit higher
大常海的比例是有點點增高
The average amount of rice our people eat is
那平均我們國人吃米的數量是
It just happens to be more successful than
剛好成就還比
fall again every year
每年再下降
Dachanghai is increased every year
大常海是每年再增加
is this possible
這是不是有這種可能
this i think
這個我想
In theory it should be possible
理論上應該是有可能
but i think
但我想
This Taiwan eats rice
這個台灣吃米量
reduce i think
減少我想
not only because
不是不只因為是
is the relationship between rice
是米的關係
but
而是
That is because you are economical
就是說因為你經濟
Development now means diversification
發展現在就是有多元化
That
那
I'm different
我倒是有不同的
that
那個
Xianghua
香華
because
因為
us
我們
the reason why m said
米之所以就是說
Also in Taiwan
也在台灣就是
that can't mean
那個不能就是說
we start over
我們重來
eat
吃
means you come back
就是說你重來
It is still enough for us to maintain the amount of rice we used to eat
我們維持以前吃米的量還是夠
that's where we put you
那就是我們要把你
The use of rice makes it diversified
米的用素把它多元化
Then why can English be used as fodder?
那其實為什麼英文可以當飼料
Why can't this text be used as fodder?
為什麼這個道文不能當飼料
So now the Council of Agriculture also has
所以現在農委會也有在
they don't like to use the word
他們不喜歡用這個字
That is to say, to develop another batch of
就是說要發展另外一批就是
Don't spend so much effort planting
你不要花這麼大力去種
That rice can be used as fodder
那米可以拿來當飼料
Taiwan imports a lot every year
我們台灣一年進口不少
Encourage it to be used as feed
鼓勵拿來做飼料
so this is
那所以這個是
Maybe doesn't directly answer your question
也許沒有直接回答你的問題
You said you want to change the rice
你說要改那個米
i think probably
我想大概是
if someone does
如果真的有人要做
should be fine
應該是沒問題的
but I use another way
但我是用另外一個方式
I think you can use it in other ways
我是覺得你可以讓它有別的用法
Because we spent a lot of foreign exchange
因為我們花了不少外匯
importing this carrier
在進口這個運民
And most people make feed outside
還有大多人在外做飼料
Now the Council of Agriculture has finally remembered
現在農委會是終於想起來了
So do they want someone now?
所以他們現在要不要人家
Hearing this word, this is called feed rice
聽到這個字,這個叫做飼料米
They eat with people because of this, they want to share the fun
他們因為這個跟人吃的,他們要有趣分
OK, thank you
OK,謝謝你
I would like to ask the host that
我想請問一下主持人就是說
Food is a global problem
糧食問題是全球問題
I always wanted to start with that green biotech
我一直想一開始那個綠色生物科技
I want to ask if there is such a concept
我想說有沒有這種概念就是說
The one that uses the animal to join its photosynthesis
把動物身上用來加入它的那個光合作用的那個
that possibility
那個可能性
animals directly form photosynthesis
就是動物直接形光合作用
like this
就像類似這樣
I think it might be a bit difficult
我想這個大概有點難
Because it photosynthesizes it has
因為它光合作用它有
In fact, the source of its gene is two sets
其實它的那個基因的來源是兩套
A set is from real and biological
一套是從真而生物來的
The other set is the continuation of the photosynthesis
另外一套是那個會光合作用的續件來的
so you just say
所以你要就說
This should be counted as the fainting of animals and plants.
經過的這個這個應該是算動植物的昏化
It should be a billion
應該是算十億
so i think you have to be in
所以我想你要在
It's kind of hard to change the consequences of this evolution right now
現在在改變這個演化的後果有點難
but you never say
但你永遠都不會說
That means we have glow fish, glow pigs
就是說我們有螢光魚 螢光豬
Are we talking about the possibility of this direction
我們是說有沒有這種方向的可能性
Fluorescent fish is actually very simple
螢光魚其實非常簡單
it's just a gene
那只是一個基因而已
fluorescent protein
會放螢光的蛋白
that is very simple
那個非常簡單
Your role of light is the whole package
你光的作用是整套的
That's the white gene
那是要上白的基因的
that might be a bit difficult
那個就可能有點難堵
But this scientific progress
但這科學的進步
I will give an example
我講一個例子
When we used to do DNA sequencing
我們以前在做DNA定序的時候
in my time
在我的年代
If you set a preface, it will be a very good PayPal
你定一個序就一篇非常好的PayPal
Some people graduate with an order
有些人畢業就是定一個序
When doing the sequencing of the human genome
那在做人的基因體的定序的時候
the god with a golden frog
那有一個金蛙的神
is the discovery of the great Boiri
就是發現大波伊里神
He said why do you want to make this order?
他說要定這個序幹什麼
He said that this sequencing technology
他說這個定序這個技術
even a monkey can do it
連猴子都可以做
At that time, it has progressed to only 20 years
那時候就已經進步到才20年
Then if you compare now with that of 20 years ago
那你現在跟那個20年前來比的話
About 1000 times better
大概進步1000倍
So that technique has bad speed
所以那個技術有壞的速度
Probably not at least 1000 times
大概至少都不只1000倍
It may be ten thousand times more
可能是上臺萬倍
So I will say No to your question
所以你的問題我現在雖然說No
但You never know
但You never know
OK
OK
thank you for his speech today
謝謝您今天他的演講
What I would like to ask is
我會想請教的是
It was mentioned at the beginning
這個一開始有說到
Swiss scientist would love to share his name
瑞士的科學家很想分享他的名
But there are some companies that he has patents and refuses to
但是有一些公司他有專利就不肯
It is also mentioned that Monsanto has many
也有提到孟山都他有很多
These related patents
這些相關的專利
But just now it was said that the international bandit democrats
那但是剛又說國際盜民主持
He'd love to open up all his bandit comments
他很希望開放他所有的盜民評論
I feel like the attitude is completely different
我覺得好像怎麼態度完全不一樣
I also heard that there is a kind of service patent in the United States.
又聽說美國有一種叫職務專利
Does that mean Taiwan is in this entire future crisis?
那是不是臺灣在這整個將來的危機裡面
Shouldn't this be the way to protect yourself?
是不是也應該使用這個方式來保護自己
Or it should not be completely open.
或是說應該不要這個完全開放比較好
There is one thing about this, you are beyond my ability, but I can tell you that when the ordering began in the early days, many individuals or companies patented their series, and they were all approved at that time.
這個有一點,你超越我的能力,不過我可以講一下,早期開始有定序的時候,有很多個人或者是公司就把他的那個系列拿去專利,那個時候都準了,
But now you only need to challenge the invalidation of those patents, because now it is what you want, you only have to sequence, that is just an information, this is useless,
但現在你只要去挑戰那些專利的無效,因為現在是你要的,你只有定序,那個只是一個information,這個都沒有用,
I think at least in our Taiwan, that is to say, the International Rice Organization, it made it, it was pre-planted, because it is an international organization, so it does not need that,
我想至少在我們台灣生,就是說國際水稻組織,它做出來的,它是種預種出來的,因為它是個國際組織,所以它不需要那個,
And it didn't use it, it didn't use the so-called fonts, that is, patented ones, but I think we need to develop in Taiwan, of course we need patents,
而且它沒有用到,沒有用到它所謂的那些栽體的,就是說有專利的,不過我覺得我們台灣要發展,當然我們要專利,
But it is used to protect ourselves, the example of Mr. Hong is very good, and our central government is also very patented, but we can be endless, that is, we don’t reward those who need tools. I think this is what we need.
但是用來是來保護我們自己,那像洪老師那個例子就是非常好的,我們中央也很專利,但我們可以無極,就是我們沒有報賞的給那些需要的工具,我想這個我們需要,
I must collect his money
我一定要收他錢
Because Jin Ming is courageous, Jin Ming belongs to Mengshan
因為黃金銘膽子黃金銘就是猛山的
The one with the most rice gene patents is also Mengshan's
水稻基因專利最多的也是猛山的
So one day we must challenge his patents
所以哪一天一定要去挑戰他那一些專利
Because he is only sequenced
因為他只是定序的而已
I think this Faguo company has its own commercial considerations
我覺得這個發國公司他有他的商業上的考量
But I guess we're scientists
不過我想我們做科學家的
It's you, you have to take the exam yourself
就是你就是有你自己考
But our country's industrial view
但我們國家的產業觀點
Or the point of view that you will solve the problem in the future
或者是你將來就要解決問題的觀點
i think i have to protect myself
我想還是要保護自己
sorry
對不起喔
But teacher, you just said that
可是老師您剛剛這樣講
If Meng Shandu develops faster
如果猛山度他研發的速度比較快
he got the patent
他拿到專利
Then we can't develop any more.
那我們就沒辦法再研發啦
Mengshantou's products are not the same
猛山頭他的產品沒有一樣
He invented it himself
是他自己發明出來的
he sold it
是他賣來的
His RUNUP was not invented by him
他的那個RUNUP不是他發明的
He studied from one university to another in New Jersey
他是從紐澤學一家一個大學
Buy him from that person
把他研那個人買去
Tell him to buy SPRS
叫他買SPRS
It's not his picture, their own research and development is not so powerful
不是他的畫面,他們自己的研發沒有那麼厲害
Because you are him in March
因為你在3月裡面的他
Because I personally do basic research
因為我個人是做基礎研究
If you do a research, you set a goal at the beginning
你如果一個研究就是一開始就設定一個目標
I must solve this problem
我一定要解決這個問題
often only ten to eighty nine you will not succeed
常常只有十至八九你不會成功
You can click, thank you teacher
可以按一下,謝謝老師
It's okay, teacher, I should be old enough
老師,沒關係,我應該是夠大了
i think because i am a middle school teacher
我想,因為我是中學老師
Then every time I come to listen to the middle school speech
那每次來聽中學的演講都
I think they will bring a lot of things back to the students in our school
我覺得都會帶很多東西回去給我們學校的學生
It's like in the future high school curriculum
那像在未來高二的課程裡面
biotechnology, there is an applied biotechnology is to explore
生物技術,有一個應用生物技術就是在探討
Give the teacher some examples of what you mentioned today
向老師您今天提到的一些例子
So I am very happy to come here to take classes
所以像來這邊上課我都很開心
You can bring many examples back to share
可以帶很多例子回去分享
I'll take a look now
那我現在就先來看一下
Please go back and share more examples
請大家多多的例子回去分享
In the past few years, I have actually listened to many courses on plant essence transplantation.
那這幾年其實我聽了很多關於植物精轉植的課程
course for teachers
幫老師的課程
So one thing I want to ask is
那我想要問的一件事情就是
Teacher, what you mentioned at the beginning is
老師你們一開頭就提到的是
In the domestic part in Taiwan
在國內 在台灣的部分
In principle, we are not allowed to
原則上根本就不是允許我們
Changed some crops
改改的一些作物
Whether it's rice
不管是水稻也好
Or what I heard at National Taiwan University
或是之前在台大聽到的
Sweet potato is also good
番薯也好
Or the tomato you just mentioned
或是您剛才提到的番茄也好
The application of stone mustard
石芥的應用
It's like what the teacher just said
那像老師剛才提到說
You want to address a lot of rice productivity decline
你想要解決很多水稻生產力下降
issues related to climate change
跟氣候變遷的問題
In the future, if you really
那將來如果您真的實質
when something like this is produced
生產出這樣的東西的時候
Isn't it going to be used in Taiwan?
不是要應用在台灣嗎
Then you are the first policy and you will get stuck
那你是第一個政策就會卡到
the second one i think
那第二個我想
It just so happens that the deputy dean is also here.
剛好那個副院長也在這邊
I don't know you
不知道你們
it's you officers
就是你們這些長官們
Is there a way to provide some input
有沒有辦法提供一些意見
How can I convince students in the future
我將來怎麼樣去說服學生
especially interested in biotechnology
特別是對生物技術有興趣
Students who want to engage in precision transplantation and application
想要從事精轉植跟應用這一塊學生
I won't go in after this one
我不會進去這一塊之後
It's great when it's done and it comes out for one thing
做完了為一個東西出來很棒
I also want to help Taiwanese
也想幫台灣人
But I'm not in Taiwan
可是我沒有在台灣
room for development
發展的空間
Here are the two questions I want to ask
這是我想要問的兩個問題
Thanks
謝謝
ok the first question is not
好 第一個問題不是
i think it should be soon
我想就是說應該很快
Our Council of Agriculture has already contacted the Department of Health
我們農委會已經跟衛生署
have already formulated these
都已經制定了這些
That is to say, genetically modified crops are pre-tests
就是說基改作物就是說前間試驗
and safety assessments and food safety assessments
還有安全評估還有食品安全評估
This policy is all here
這個政策都在這裡
The next stage is to say
下一個階段就是說
Do you want quasi-GM crops to go on the market?
要不要準基改作物上市
I want to say that after all these years of discussion
我想就說經過大家這幾年來的討論
my prediction is
我的預計是會
In the beginning, it was likely that the main Taiwanese
一開始很可能是台灣籍的主要
I don't think the water is right
我想水到不會準
But the others, especially the Fahui
但是其他幾個尤其是發會的話
It should be right, just like a fluorescent fish
應該會準 像螢光魚就準
So I think the main thing is
所以我想最主要就是
This is not just a Taiwan problem
這不只是台灣的問題
In Europe, genetically modified crops are not allowed to be
像歐洲的話基改作物根本不準正
So let the Americans rule the world
所以讓美國人獨霸天下
that this but you too I guess it's a comparison
那這個 但你也 我想這是比較
This is tantamount to being a member of politics and society
這是等於是政治跟社會的成員
Then I'm not that desperate
那我並沒有那麼那個 desperate
i think it should
我想應該會
That is to say, you, especially I think we scientists also have a part of our responsibility
就是說你尤其我想我們科學家也有一部人的責任
Because when we go out to talk to that, that is to say, society, this is
因為我們出去跟那個就是說社會這個就是
The one who is equal to the dialogue is not so enthusiastic
等於對話的那個並沒有那麼踴躍
I think this is you Taiwan is a democratic country
我想這是你 台灣是個民主國家
You want a policy, this is actually a pretty big policy
你要一個政策 這個其實是一個蠻重大的政策
I think you should just say
我想你應該就是說
Although I know I know it's a good thing
雖然我知道 我知道這個是好的事
But you still have to be able to convince the society
但你還是要能夠說服這個社會
Most of the general public will accept you as this
大部分的社會大眾來接受你這個
Then I think Taiwan can be smart
那我想台灣能夠聰明
I think you have a conversation that should work out
我想你有對話應該可以解決
And our government should say they
而且我們的政府應該也就是說他們
At least two years ago the attitude started
最近至少最近兩年的態度就開始
I was talking about that at the beginning
本來一開始就是說那個那個
the constitutional one
憲政的那個
The chairman of the Council of Agriculture and the chairman of the vice-chairman Cai Bing will not
農委會主委還有副主委會財兵會長也不會
now that is to say
現在已經就是說
Because their considerations are not scientific objections at all.
因為他們的考量完全不是科學上的反對
but political considerations
而是政治上的考量
I think this can be resolved through dialogue.
那這個我想可以靠對話來解決
should come
應該會來
I think most of the regulations are already in the Executive Yuan
我想大部分的法規都已經在行政院了
So wait for another discussion now
所以現在就等另外一個討論
Then maybe in a few years
然後說不定再幾年就會
At least we all have these quizzes
至少這些測驗的我們都有
Then there are laws
那就法規都有
So I guess if there's interest I guess it should
所以我想如果有興趣我想應該
at least become a scientist
至少成為一個科學家
It is a very important report field
本身就是一個很重要的餘握的報場
I think this and the others are probably
我想這個其他的大概都是
It's the newsroom of the guardian
都是護家的那個報場
Thank you, thank you Mayor for your wonderful speech
謝謝 謝謝市主任的精彩演講
My personal question is related to the previous question
我個人的提問跟前一個問題是有關聯性
Then the mayor mentioned in the report that
然後市主任在報告中有提到一點
This is the development of biotechnology
就是這個生物科技的發展
One thing that needs to be considered is the impact on the ecology
有一點需要肯算就是對生態的影響
We know that in Europe and America
我們曉得在歐美
It has a very important role in the development of biotechnology
它發展生物科技有很重要的一番
That is to say, to engage in the so-called Tianjian experiment
就是說要從事所謂的天堅試驗
Inmimental Release
Inmimental Release
Because in this biomodified crop
因為在這個生改農作物
Before licensing
許可上市之前
So I don't know that in our country
所以我不曉得說在我國
If you are engaged in the development of biotechnology
如果說從事生物科技的發展
Is it necessary to engage in the so-called big sky experiment?
是不是也必須從事所謂的大天試驗
this is my problem thanks
這是我的問題 謝謝
we have this rule
我們是有這個規定
Taiwan now has two
現在台灣有兩個
Actually there are several stages
其實有幾個階段
One is your small field experiment
一個就是你小規模的田間的試驗
Now the South Center of Academia Sinica, Chung Hsing University
現在中興大學中研院的南部中心
There are also farms with this facility
還有農事所都有這個設施
That means you can do small-scale facilities for genetically modified crops
就是說你可以做基改作物的小規模的設施
Then the large scale you mentioned is only owned by the Central University and the Farming Department.
那你講的大規模只有中心大學跟農事所有
Now that's the papaya I was talking about
那現在就是我剛剛講的那個木瓜
Teacher Ye Xidong's papaya is already doing experiments at this stage
葉錫東老師的木瓜已經在做這個階段的試驗
Mr. Chen Nongwang's frog dishes are still being made on a small scale
那陳農王老師的青蛙菜還在做小規模的
windy
有風靈的
so yes we have
所以是有的 我們是有的
It is only because the regulations for genetically modified crops to be marketed have really matured in the past two years
只是因為基改作物要上市的法規是這兩年才真的成熟
Now it’s still called the Chief, and it’s still called the Draft in the Executive Yuan.
現在還叫長在行政院還叫草案
but he already said
但是他已經就是說
Because you have farmers though the market for papaya is mainly in India
因為你雖然農有木瓜的市場主要是在印度
India still has to see you in Taiwan before he accepts it
印度還是要看到你台灣準的他才會接受
So our Council of Agriculture has taken this into consideration
所以我們農委會有考慮到這個
So now there is a set here
所以現在是有一套在這裡
So that instruction you said
所以你說的那個指示
This problem also exists for other machine modification linkages.
對於其他的機改聯動也都有這個問題
there is a problem here
這邊有問題
Now in the market I see
現在在市面上我看到
I see in the market later
以後我在市面上我看到
In short, it will become less and less
總之會越來越少
Just one of the models before
就之前在機種的一個經過
Modified machine
經過調整過的機改
So in terms of biodiversity
那這樣在生物多樣性方面
from this icon
就要從這個圖示
The second question is that you need to say
那第二個問題是你需要說
Mention does not have to
提到並不一定要
to be in the model
要在機種裡面
They are all in the machine, mainly for themselves
都在機種裡面主要是為了自己
reduced one re-open
減少的一個重開
Then you mentioned that yes
那你又提到說是
you mentioned again
你又提到說是
If it is said to be a successful usage in this press
如果說是在這個按到的成功用法
just use that
就用那個打走
Why can't we use our current adoption method
為什麼不能說用我們現在的那個採用法
exist
在
super far one that is pressed
超遠一個那個按到的
say the method used
說採用的方法
Then use the method
那再用採用方法
or a poker
或者是一個打牌
can be in that kind of
可以在那一種
at this
在這個
in sweep usage
在掃取用法
Second, if we talk about those few things, what are they?
那二來說如果說那些少的什麼來
OK that
OK 那個
The first question is whether it will affect biodiversity
第一個問題就是說會不會影響生物多樣性
because
因為
all
所有的
Because of the GMOs you made
因為你做的這些基改的那個做物
probably have a market
大概都是要有market
so you should be all
所以你應該都是
so-called making
所謂的做物
In fact, the object itself is a
那其實那個做物本身就是一個
one
一個
This is what you plant in a unit area
就是你在一個單位面積裡面種的就是這一種
So I don't think it should affect the so-called
所以我想不應該會影響到所謂的
biodiversity
生物多樣性
Our diversity is actually
我們的多樣性是其實是
it's not us
不是我們在在
There's no variety, you're just one of those kinds
沒有什麼多樣性,你就是那幾種而已
So I guess it shouldn't be a big problem
所以我想這個應該不是很大的問題
As for that
至於就是說
I think it means why are you so watery?
我想就是說你水到為什麼
Just don't use water, why not use that cauliflower
就是不用水,為什麼不用那個菜花
I think it's cost related
我想這個成本有關的
It is how much labor you need to spend, how much you can plant
就是要花多少勞力,你才能夠種多少那個
Like the way of American Chinese artists
像美國中藝民他種的方式
He is completely mechanical, he is very dense
他就是完全機械了,他就種很密
So the species he encountered was
所以他遇出來的種就是
That is, he can only go up, but not bend
就是他只會往上漲,就是不會彎曲
So what kind of disaster do you want?
所以說你要什麼樣的災別方式
what kind do you want
你就要什麼樣的種
i want this
我想這個
What we call a crop, his competitive
我們所謂的作物,他的競爭性
Actually not very big
其實都不是很大
So when you get water, you use water to help him
所以你水到,你用水來幫助他的話
let him grow up well
讓他可以長得很好
he's used to it
那他已經適應了
That is to say, in fact, we humans have been planting water for almost 10,000 years.
就是說其實水到我們人類已經種了快一萬年
So I guess the ones that are more popular now
所以我想現在比較流行的那幾個
Maybe I said it doesn't need water to live
大概我說它不需要水可以活
just say it can live
只是說它可以活
But its competitiveness is not necessarily so strong
但它的競爭力就不見得那麼強
So I guess there is still a need for a new flat tide
所以我想還是有需要新的平潮
As for the problems of miscellaneous tides
至於就是雜潮這些問題
I think this is roughly
我想這個大概比較
with the technical aspects of agriculture that we have now
以我們現在有的農業的技術方面
It should be possible to cultivate
應該可以是可以用栽培的方式
So I have a final
所以我前面那邊有一個最後
We want to be equal to our new technology
我們要等於是我們的新技術
plus that cultivation
再加上那個栽培
Is it possible to have a set of platforms to do it?
是不是可以有一套的平台來做
I don't know if this answers your question
我不知道這樣子有沒有回答你的問題
I want to ask the teacher
我想請教老師
It's about reproductive energy.
就是關於生殖能源方面的問題
Teacher, we just mentioned today
老師今天剛剛我們也提到
It's because there seem to be many more
就是因為其實好像還有很多
Technology to break down living things to do
分解生物的技術要做
What is the teacher
請問老師是
Do you think, for example, Higher Brand or MicroRG
你覺得 譬如說是Higher Brand或是MicroRG
Which one does the teacher think is more likely to be commercialized in the future?
哪一種是老師覺得比較有可能 未來有可能商業化的
Also, what research technologies must be done before commercialization
還有就是離商業化 還有哪些研究技術是必須要做
Then we can do business
然後才能做到商業的話
I think the problem has two
我想這個問題有兩個
The first question he asked was to say
第一個就是 他問的問題就是說
Because we have a team of researchers, including Wang Wuyuan
因為我們中研員有一個團隊 包括王務院
We are doing reproductive agriculture in a pretty big team
我們在一個蠻大的團隊在做生殖農業
What we do in reproductive agriculture is the second generation
那生殖農業我們做的是第二代
That is, we don't use electrograin to ferment, but to make alcohol
就是我們不是用電紋來發酵 要來做酒精
We use plant cell currency
我們是用植物的細胞幣
That is to say, some people say that plants can dance
就是說等於有些人說用植物會起舞
To make it cell money, cell money is mainly cellulose and pie cellulose
要把它細胞幣 細胞幣最主要是纖維素跟派纖維素
Convert it to brassan for your flower effect
把它轉變為布拉桑讓你花效
I think this technique should work
這個技術我想是應該做得到
The other is the source of cell coins
另外一個就是細胞幣的來源
If someone tells you that the agricultural association can let you use it as the main source of alcohol
如果有人跟你說農業會企務可以讓你拿來做最主要的酒精的來源
You tell him to do the math
你叫他算一算
If you really want to use reproduction to make alcohol
你如果真的要用生殖來做酒精
you must have reproductive crops
你一定要有生殖作物
talking crops
就是能言作物
You can't just rely on agriculture and corporate affairs
你不能只靠農業會企務不夠
if you really want to replace
你如果真的要取代
For example, 230% of Petronas
譬如說要國家石油百分之二十三十
You must be an eloquent crop
你絕對要做能言作物
You can't say that relying on agriculture will lead to business
你不能說靠農業會企務
Then I also object to using Dao sense to make alcohol
那我也要反對用道感來做酒精
Because Taiwanese farmers have their own reasons for feeling burned.
因為臺灣農民燒道感是有他的道理
because he returns nutrients to the land
因為他把養分回歸土地
He burned the second one
第二個他燒一燒
In fact, it can be said that the soil inside
其實是可以就是說把土裡面的
Burnt from soft or something
從的軟什麼的燒光
So although they are air pollution
所以他們雖然是空氣汙
There is air pollution
有空氣汙軟
Then this is what you want to evaluate
那這個就是你要評估
But if you really put all your sense of Tao
但你如果真的把所有的道感
take it all
通通拿過來
First, your cost is definitely not enough
第一你的成本絕對不夠
Because Taiwan is all small farmers
因為台灣都是小農
so you take the sense
所以你拿道感
To gather together to do even nine thousand
要集中在一起做甚至九千
You don't have enough money for the first one
那第一個你成本不夠
the second you will
第二個你就是會
Your nutrients did not return to that land
你那些養分沒有回歸那個土地
So your question I think is
所以你的問題我覺得就是
you must have energy crops
你一定要有能源作物
Taiwan land in small
台灣土地在小
Don't Make Your Own Energy Crops
不要自己做能源作物
we develop technology
我們發展技術
After your technology matures,
你這一套技術成熟以後
see if you can do that
你看能不能做那個
but i think you really want alternative energy
但是我想你真的要替代能源
Early class I want variety
早類我想要多樣性
you can't just rely on
你不可以就只靠
For example, if you only rely on a certain energy crop
比如說你只靠某一種能源作物
Of course everyone is groping now
那當然現在大家都在摸索
The second generation of that even energy technology
第二代的那個甚至能源的技術
so if you want
所以你要的話
Taiwan will be like the people
台灣會像國民
have enough scientific energy
有足夠的科學能量
So we should develop more
所以我們就應該多研發
If you want to develop even without
如果要發展甚至沒有
do a few first
先做幾個
And take the road of technological development
而且走技術發展的路
Then when the time comes, you actually have the key technology
然後到時候其實你有關鍵技術
Research material is not
研料不是
That is, if other places can
就是說如果別的地方可以
can want
可以要
you have technology
你有技術
Your research is definitely a problem
你研料絕對是個問題
So I think what we want to develop in Taiwan is the middle section
所以我想我們台灣要發展的是中間這一段
technology
就是技術
next our children
接下來我們兒女
What about everyone?
各位呢
Where
在哪裡
our disorder
我們 disorder
Plant a tree in ten years and turn it into a tree in a year
十年种树把它变成一年种树
If you think this tree can grow and be used in one year
觉得一年这个树能成长能利用的话
Then I think the development of existing energy is a very breakthrough
那么我想对已经能源的开发是非常的突破
The second is that there was a newspaper report recently that
那第二个是近来有个报纸报道就是
Abroad is already researching something
国外已经在研究一个东西
called artificial leaves
叫做 artificial leaves
It is said that only God can make leaves
说上帝才可以造树叶
But now people can already make leaves
可是现在人已经可以造树叶
Then this leaf is made
那么这个树叶造出来
It can accept light
它可以接受光芙中
Then it can be generated
那因此就可以产生
even a mimic leaf
甚至一个模仿的树叶
When it passes through the American Department
它经过有族美系里的时候
both sides of its leaves
它的树叶的两面
One side is to divide water into green and oxygen
一面是把水分成青和氧
one side is green
一面是青
one side is oxygen
一面是氧
In this way, the oxygen can be separated
这样的话就可以氧分开了
Then of course it can change
然后当然就可以发变
So its ideal is to say
所以它这个理想就是说
Ordinary households can take advantage of this technology
普通的家庭可以利用这个技术
workers to their own power
工给自己的电源
two topics
两个题目啊
One is a bit earlier
一个是比较前一点的
time book report
时间的书的报道
one is a newspaper report that came in
一个是进来的报纸报道
Then these two questions
那么这两个问题
I don't know what's inside our courtyard
不知道我们院里面
Have you thought about it in this direction?
有没有向这个方向来想
Thanks
谢谢
I can answer the first question
第一个问题我可以回答
i think nature
我想自然界
is there such a number
是有这种数
Number of developments
发扬数
He grows several meters a year
他一年就长好几公尺
so in
所以在
Northern Europe and Australia
北欧还有澳洲
They've put the number in order
他们已经把这个数给定序
then they
然后他们
Also take this as an eloquent crop
也拿这个来当能言作物
There are also word making materials
还有造词的材料
so
所以
have we ever thought
我们有没有想过
have
有
But we don't think about counting
但我们想的不是数
we want basket flowers
我们想的是篮花
Because the basket flowers from that
因为篮花从那个
Get out of that organization
从那个组织配昂出来
I'm going to that seedling again
又要到那个成苗
almost two years
要快两年
Then why does he grow so fast
那他为什么生长的速度
so slow
这么慢
then we use this
那我们是以这个
basic science perspective
基础科学的眼光
come and see this
来看这件事
but
但是
Some blue parks in the south are interested in hearing us do this
南部的一些藍園聽我們做這個有興趣
They said whether to cooperate with the industry association
他們就說要不要產協合作
This is still far from cooperation
這個離產協合作還很遠
All we have to ask is why butterfly blue
我們要問的就是為什麼蝴蝶藍
the rate at which its cells divide
它的細胞分裂的速度
That is to say it grows so slowly
就是說它成長的速度這麼慢
why two years
為什麼要兩年
Because some varieties of blue flowers do not need a year
因為有些藍花的品種不需要就一年
It can be from planting flower buds to fruiting
它就可以從種植花芽到結果
so we are thinking
所以我們是有在想
but we are thinking
但是我們在想
In fact, if you say that you are not affected by the industry, you are lying.
其實如果說沒有受產業影響也是騙你的
because we people ask us
因為我們人家問我們
that is, can you do this
就是說你們能不能做這個
so we start thinking
所以我們就開始思考
so we're thinking
所以我們就有在想
This is actually a very difficult problem
這個其實是一個非常難的問題
Because this question is for people who are doing plants
因為這個問題是在做植物的人
This question is rarely asked
很少去問的這個問題
That is to say, your cells divide in the plant body
就是說你細胞分裂的在植物體
how to be controlled
怎麼樣被控制
and the growth of its cells
還有它細胞的成長
Cell Size Control
細胞大小的控制
this is rarely done
這個很少人做
so we are thinking
所以我們是有在想
naturally
自然是
And there is this diversity
而且是有這個多樣性存在
So this is an interesting success problem
所以這個是一個很有趣的成功問題
this i think will do
這個我想會做
it is possible and someone is thinking
是可能而且有人在想
The second question is to compare
第二個問題就比較
Also a bit out of my field
也有一點超過我的領域
because i know someone who was
因為我知道有人曾經
Because of this light ear effect
因為這個光耳作用
You said that this leaf should have oxygen and water
這個葉子你說要讓它有氧氣跟水
that actually
那個其實
The process itself is not so simple
它本身那個process不是那麼簡單的
there is that
那是有那個
have nobel prize winners
有諾貝爾獎得主
just do that
就是做那個
The electronic group component of the karmic body
業力體的那個電子團體件
that it is predicted
那它是有預測
That is to say, it is possible to do this
就是說可以做這個方面的事
But I haven't at least in science
但是我還沒有至少在科學
That is to say, I don't know which newspaper to read.
就是說我不知道看是哪一報
at least in this
至少在這個
I don't know if the internet has seen it
我不知道網路有沒有看過
That is to say, this aspect of the article
就是說這一方面的文章
then we can go back
那我們倒是可以回去
look at this aspect
看看這個方面
I can only tell you today that I don't know
今天只能跟你說我不知道
probably still some distance
大概還有一段距離
still some distance
還有一段距離
are there any other questions
還有沒有什麼其他的問題
there is one over there
那邊有一位
Hello, teacher. I am the student of this year's position.
老師你好 我是今年職位所的那個屬其生
then i want to ask
那我想請問一下
Is that I'm subservient to the front until now down
就是我從屬其要正面到現在下來
Actually I have been having a problem
其實我一直有一個問題
That is to say, when we are doing genetic modification
就是說我們在做基因改良的時候
That's when we were doing Trims Form
就是我們在做Trims Form的時候
why can't we say
為什麼我們沒有辦法說
It's the one that let the farmer plant it
就是讓農民他種下去的那個
genetically modified plants
做的基因改良植物
the first offspring
種出來的那個第一子代
There is no way to continue to produce a second offspring
沒辦法再繼續產生第二子代
Is there any other issue involved?
這是不是有牽扯到什麼其他的問題
because i knew it was
因為我就知道是說
We have this technology in
我們有這個技術在
But it seems there is no way to do it
可是好像就是沒辦法去做
You say you want them to have only the first offspring
你就說要讓他們只能有第一個子代
But I can't go down and plant myself
但不能再往下自己收植自己
Yes because it is to avoid
對 因為就是避免
because when we choose
因為我們在做選擇的時候
we are usually in
我們通常都會在裡面
and some other antibiotic genes
再加入一些其他的抗生素的基因
If we want to avoid the spread of its genes
那如果說想要避免它的基因擴散的話
Does that mean that it cannot produce a second generation?
那是不是說讓它沒辦法再產生第二次代
This approach should be better
這個做法應該會比較好一點
I think it should be theoretically possible to do so
我想應該理論上是可以這樣做的
But that means you can put
但就是說你可以把
You can have this mechanism of marriage paper
你可以有這種婚紙的機制
you can even put
你可以甚至把
I think in theory you could
我想理論上你可以
That is to say, the gene jumped out in the second generation
就是說在第二代那個基因就跳出來
should be no problem
應該沒問題
should theoretically be able to do
應該理論上可以做
It's just that I think most of it, at least I think it means
只是我想大部分的至少我覺得就是說
The way I tell you is
我跟像你說的方法就是
That Meng Shantou they are controlling
那個蒙山頭他們在控制
because they sold that seed
因為他們賣了那個種子
They don't want the farmers to harvest the seeds themselves and plant them again
他們就不要農民自己去收種子再種
Don't buy seeds from him
就不跟他買種子了
So they're a farmer with you
所以他們就跟你們一個農民
How many seeds do you plant a year and he takes pictures of you
你一年種多少顆他把你照相
If you didn’t buy many seeds from him in the second year, he will sue you
你第二年沒有跟他買多少種子他就告你
if you plant it
如果你種出來
You planted more seeds than you bought from him
你種出來比你跟他買的種子還要多
he will sue you
他就去告你
How many other farmers have been paid millions of dollars
有還有多少農民被賠了幾百萬美金
I just turned him upside down
我剛好把他倒過來
i think you planted
我覺得你種了
If you want to give to the peasants, you should give to the peasants
你要給農民就應該給農民
As long as it is your own designed savings
只要就是你自己設計出來的存錢
Without the possibility of environmental pollution
要沒有這個環境污染的可能性
because your first generation
因為你第一代
if you are afraid
你如果怕
I am afraid that the second generation and the first generation should not go out.
怕第二代你第一代就不應該出去了
I think the businessman gave us three heads, of course he would like to have this
我想生意人給我們三頭他當然希望有這種
put me right upside down
讓我剛好倒過來
This second generation like the recent
這個第二代的像最近
glowfish they quadruple him
螢光魚他們把他弄成四倍級
he won't pass it down
他就不會往下傳
Otherwise, if your fish is sold, they will keep raising it
不然你魚賣出去了人家就一直養
don't do your business
你生意就不要做了
Yes, different considerations
對就是不同的考量
But farmers are stronger, so it should be
但農民比較強所以應該就
ok so last two questions
好 那最後兩個問題
Excuse me, sir, I have a very simple question for you
不好意思 主任請教你一個非常簡單的問題
That's our one, we're only talking about rice now
就是說我們那個 我們現在只談到稻米
Is there a way to turn vegetables from aerobic respiration
那有沒有辦法把蔬菜 青菜從有氧呼吸
Switch to anaerobic respiration, so you won't be afraid of typhoons
轉為無氧呼吸 那這樣就不怕颱風來
it's all rotten thanks
才都爛掉 謝謝
I mean, switch to aerobic, switch to anaerobic
就說 轉成有氧 轉成無氧
All plants will have proof for you
所有的植物都會 都有證明給你
So it should be some other mechanism
所以它應該是有別的機制
It can't be filled for a long time
它沒有辦法補了比較久
the vegetables our next step is
那蔬菜 我們下一步就是
we make rice from that
我們從那個做水稻
And do the so-called Arab world, learned
還有做所謂阿拉伯界 學到了
we are going to start now
我們現在就是要開始
talks about cutting plants
會談到切割的植物
We Taiwanese farmers are actually very smart
我們台灣農民其實很聰明
we haven't invented yet
我們還沒有發明
They have come up with some solutions
他們已經想出一些解決的方法
they put that
他們把那個
It's just that it's not easy to change money.
就是換錢比較不抗原水
Some are actually very antigenic
有些其實非常抗原水
They use cheap
他們就用價街的
so you don't have to do anything
所以你就不用再做什麼
It's good to change chicken to beans
雞改豆這樣就好
And our farmers in Taiwan are very powerful
而且我們台灣農民非常厲害
They can even mechanize the price street
他們連價街都可以機械化
So how many hundreds of dollars do you want to buy from him?
所以你跟他要買多少幾百個價街的那個苗
I'll give it to you in a week
一個禮拜以後就給你們
So I buy from them for experiments
所以我做實驗都跟他們買
I don't have to go by myself
我不用自己走
So some farmers are better than me
所以有些農民比我厲害
so vegetables are
所以蔬菜是
vegetables are better
蔬菜比較好
Because vegetables usually if they are leafy vegetables
因為蔬菜通常如果是葉菜的話
you want leaves
你就是要葉子
So use the price street method
所以用價街的方法
Our Taiwanese bitter gourd and loofah
我們台灣苦瓜還有絲瓜
This is all solved by this
這個都是靠這個解決
But when the typhoon came, the leafy vegetables were all destroyed.
可是葉菜類那個颱風一來就整個都
right so
對所以
The problem is that in fact
那問題是其實就是說
If you let it become antigenic water
你如果讓它變成抗原水
probably means
很可能就是說
often some are
常常有一些就是
make it look bad
會讓它長得不太好
That is to say, what you gain is what you lose
就是說你有一得必有一失
import a feature
引進一個特性
it tends to
它往往會
But what we're thinking now is that this mechanism is
但是我們現在有在想就是這種機制是
It only activates when you're flooded
你淹水的時候它才啟動
It's not like water until those mechanisms are always there
不是像水到那些機制一直都在
so we are thinking
所以我們是有在想
Vegetables may be simpler than water
蔬菜可能比水到要簡單的
Because usually we resolve by saying
因為通常我們化解就是說
You change to anaerobic and non-inhalation method
你改無氧無吸法
A gene is expressed more
一個基因表現得比較多
it's more stuck
它就比較卡
so this is ok
所以這個是可以
so only when i come back
所以只是我回來以後
never thought of doing this
一直沒有想到去做這種事
Running every time a typhoon comes
每次颱風來才都跑騰
I'm thinking about it now
對我現在有想到這個事
So we'll start doing that
所以我們會開始做這一方面
Thanks
謝謝
and the last one
還有最後一位
Supost let me ask a question
Supost我來請教一個
Questions that might stray from your topic today
可能偏離今天你主題的問題
It is about the market supply and demand of food
就是有關糧食的市場供需的問題
I am a Meng Yichang
我是一個孟宜昌
Now seven or eight years ago in Taiwan we had that except bemi
現在在七八年前台灣我們有那個除貝米
That surplus of old rice is almost going to the shop
那個舊米過剩差不多要操舖去
Encourage soldiers and college students to eat more rice
鼓勵阿兵哥還有大學生多吃米
at that time
那個時候正好
The welfare soldiers are short of about 2.8 million tons of 10 meters
福利兵一連缺了大概280萬噸的10米
It was time for the overworked President of Asda
那個時候是去做過勞的阿斯達總統
I used to do business at that time
那個時候我就曾經做過生意
At that time, I loved Taiwan and wanted to sell this rice there.
那時候我愛台灣想要把這個米能夠銷到那邊去
Turns out Taiwan is very bureaucratic
結果台灣很官僚
All of a sudden, the Central Trust Bureau by bidding
一下子用招標那次中央信託局
It's only 10,000 to 20,000 tons at a time
是一次是標一兩萬噸而已
And I have to Zengxun, pack and transport
而且我自己還要增勳還要包裝還要運輸
wow that's tiring so i'm from vietnam
哇那很累所以我就從越南
They're all packed and shipped to the next one for sale there.
他們都包裝好再下一個運到銷到那邊去
So just now you mentioned again
所以剛剛你再有提起說
Welfare soldiers can do three goods in a row, right?
福利兵一連可以三貨是不是
There should be no shortage of rice
應該不會缺米才對阿
Why is he still missing more than two million tons in a row?
為什麼他還一連缺了兩百多萬噸
that currently
那目前
I don't know if there is any improvement, I don't know
不曉得有沒有改善我不曉得
These people, my master, can come to ask you for advice
這些人我師父可以來請教你
Why
為什麼
Let's just say go to the International Waterways Center every year
我們就說每年都去國際水道中心
At dusk, the International Waterway Center is at Huilibin
黃昏 國際水道中心就是在惠里濱
so they feel ashamed
所以他們就覺得很丟臉
The world's best waterway research center
世界最好的水道研究中心
Every year in Huilibin
在惠里濱就惠里濱每年
In fact, when it is politically stable
那其實在它政治安定的時候
not like this
不是這樣子
Huilibin is actually very rich in nature.
惠里濱其實是自然自然非常豐富
He has no reason not to be autonomous
他沒有理由不能自己自主
so it's a matter of politics
所以這是政治的問題
rather than an economic or agricultural issue
而不是經濟或農業的問題
because of their social policy
因為跟他們社會政策
Nearby their rich and poor
他們那個貧富附近還有
right
對
If you want the government to have a heart
像你要政府有心的話
Like Vietnam becoming the second largest in the world within a few years
像越南在幾年以內變成世界第二大
the rice exporting country
那個稻米的輸出國
You can see they use
你可以看到他們用的
the technology they use
他們用的技術
I'm with that silent teacher
我跟那個補無聲老師就是
COA wants us to evaluate them
農委會要我們去評估他們
because of them
因為他們
because
因為
WTO relationship we have to import 6% of rice every year
WTO的關係我們每年要進口6%的稻米
so we buy it ourselves
所以我們自己購
Taiwan has always sold in the United States
那台灣一直都在美國賣
Recently, Vietnam has been selling
最近越南一直要賣
then we are
那我們是
The rice imported from the United States we are
美國進口的米我們是
Sampling
抽檢
Vietnamese rice we are
越南的米我們是
Check each batch
每批檢查
The Council of Agriculture wants us to go
農委會要我們去
look at him
看他的
the one you produced
你生產的那個
When we came back from that process, we suggested to him that we should come back.
那個過程回來跟他建議我們回來的建議還是
Continue to check without package
繼續沒包收檢
That
那
So but as long as the country has that, they are very labor-intensive
所以但是你只要國家有那個他們是非常花很多的勞力
So their current rice
所以他們現在的米
Even though the quality is not good
就說雖然品質不好
but they have enough
但他們量夠多
There's no reason not to do well
那會裡面沒有理由不做好
That's his social structure and his political problems
那就是他的社會結構還有他的政治問題
this
這個
no one can help
沒有人可以幫忙
only themselves
只有他們自己
they have the best
他們有最好的
world
世界
best waterway
最好的水道
The research center is just at Rose Beach, just at the establishment of diplomatic relations in Marilla, he has no reason to do it
研究中心,就在玫瑰濱的,就在馬里拉的建交,他沒有理由做過
Moreover, there are thousands of islands, and the lack of thousands of islands is really
而且有幾千個島,幾千個島竟然的缺乎,實在是
More than two million tons a year
一年兩百多萬噸
Every time you go to our Guojin rice center, you are really bad
每次去就下我們國進水稻中心,你們實在是很糟糕
no split price
沒有分裂價
Well, thanks, we actually I have two observations that I have today
好,謝謝,我們其實我有兩個觀察,我今天
see so many people come to listen
看到有這麼多人來聽
It can be seen that everyone is interested in these agricultural
可見大家對這些農業
The topic is also very concerned, I think it's pretty good
議題也是很關心,我覺得蠻不錯的
Without agriculture, we would have no food, this is very serious
這個沒有農業,我們就沒有飯吃,這個很嚴重
So this another
所以這個另外一個
What the mayor didn't talk about, what he just said
這個市主任沒有談到的,剛才講
farmers these our technology is very good and so on
農民這些我們的技術很好等等
but
但是
how do we do this
這個我們怎麼
Actually just with this
其實剛才跟這個
The fact that the second generation is not long has a little bit to do with how we protect our own sanctions
第二代不長的這個也有一點點關係,就是我們怎麼樣子來保護我們自己的制裁
It's a good thing developed.
開發出來的很好的東西啊
Unfortunately, many kinds of sneaks are now
很不幸的,現在很多種種偷跑
then run across from us
那跑到我們的對面去
Then grow something and sell it to us
然後把東西種出來賣給我們
this is also a problem
這個也是一個問題
So in this new species you make
所以在這個你做出來的新的種
or these things
或者是這些東西
how do we protect ourselves
我們怎麼自己保護住
If you can have this idea
能夠有這種觀念的話
Then he will use this thing
那以後他要用這個東西
we can take his money
我們就可以抽他的錢
so we can make more money to
所以我們就可以賺更多的錢來
Otherwise, Taiwan will have problems in the future
要不然這個台灣將來有問題
we are so small
我們自己地那麼小
no way to compete
沒有辦法競爭
well, thank you very much for coming
好,非常感謝各位的來參加
thank you
謝謝各位